<worldheritage promo="UNESCO">
<row id="698" unique="826" trans="0" lat="-19.08333333" long="138.71666670">
    <criteria>(viii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>States of Queensland and South Australia</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Australian Fossil Mammal Sites (Riversleigh / Naracoorte)</site>
    <description>Riversleigh and Naracoorte, situated in the north and south respectively of eastern Australia, are among the world’s 10 greatest fossil sites. They are a superb illustration of the key stages of evolution of Australia's unique fauna.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="166" unique="1457" trans="0" lat="-33.85666667" long="151.21527778">
    <criteria>(i)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>New South Wales</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Sydney Opera House</site>
    <description>Inaugurated in 1973, the Sydney Opera House is listed as a great architectural work of the 20th century that brings together multiple strands of creativity and innovation, both in architectural form and structural design. A great urban sculpture set in a remarkable waterscape, at the tip a peninsula projecting into Sydney Harbour, the building has had an enduring influence on architecture. The Opera House comprises three groups of interlocking vaulted ‘shells&amp;#39; which roof two main performances halls and a restaurant. These shell-structure are set upon a vast platform and are surrounded by terrace areas that function as pedestrian concourses. In 1957, when the project of the Sydney opera was attributed by an international jury to the then almost unknown Danish architect Jørn Utzon, it marked a radically new and collaborative approach to construction. In listing the building, the Sydney Opera House is recognized as a great artistic monument accessible to society at large.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="608" unique="722" trans="0" lat="-6.75000000" long="105.33333330">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>id</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Provinces of Banten (formerly West Java) and Lampung</location>
    <state>Indonesia</state>
    <site>Ujung Kulon National Park</site>
    <description>This national park, located in the extreme south-western tip of Java on the Sunda shelf, includes the Ujung Kulon peninsula and several offshore islands and encompasses the natural reserve of Krakatoa. In addition to its natural beauty and geological interest – particularly for the study of inland volcanoes – it contains the largest remaining area of lowland rainforests in the Java plain. Several species of endangered plants and animals can be found there, the Javan rhinoceros being the most seriously under threat.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1013" unique="1183" trans="0" lat="4.13333000" long="114.91667000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>my</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>northern Sarawak, island of Borneo</location>
    <state>Malaysia</state>
    <site>Gunung Mulu National Park</site>
    <description>Important both for its high biodiversity and for its karst features, Gunung Mulu National Park, on the island of Borneo in the State of Sarawak, is the most studied tropical karst area in the world. The 52,864-ha park contains seventeen vegetation zones, exhibiting some 3,500 species of vascular plants. Its palm species are exceptionally rich, with 109 species in twenty genera noted. The park is dominated by Gunung Mulu, a 2,377 m-high sandstone pinnacle. At least 295 km of explored caves provide a spectacular sight and are home to millions of cave swiftlets and bats. The Sarawak Chamber, 600 m by 415 m and 80 m high, is the largest known cave chamber in the world.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="502" unique="586" trans="0" lat="17.57500000" long="120.38750000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>ph</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Province of Ilocos Sur</location>
    <state>Philippines</state>
    <site>Historic Town of Vigan</site>
    <description>Established in the 16th century, Vigan is the best-preserved example of a planned Spanish colonial town in Asia. Its architecture reflects the coming together of cultural elements from elsewhere in the Philippines, from China and from Europe, resulting in a culture and townscape that have no parallel anywhere in East and South-East Asia.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="652" unique="773" trans="0" lat="10.16666667" long="118.91666670">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>ph</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Palawan Province</location>
    <state>Philippines</state>
    <site>Puerto-Princesa Subterranean River National Park</site>
    <description>This park features a spectacular limestone karst landscape with an underground river. One of the river's distinguishing features is that it emerges directly into the sea, and its lower portion is subject to tidal influences. The area also represents a significant habitat for biodiversity conservation. The site contains a full 'mountain-to-sea' ecosystem and has some of the most important forests in Asia.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="653" unique="774" trans="0" lat="8.96667000" long="120.00000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>ph</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Palawan , Region 4</location>
    <state>Philippines</state>
    <site>Tubbataha Reef Marine Park</site>
    <description>The Tubbataha Reef Marine Park covers 33,200 ha, including the North and South Reefs. It is a unique example of an atoll reef with a very high density of marine species; the North Islet serveing as a nesting site for birds and marine turtles. The site is an excellent example of a pristine coral reef with a spectacular 100-m perpendicular wall, extensive lagoons and two coral islands.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="854" unique="1005" trans="0" lat="-11.68333000" long="160.33333000">
    <criteria>(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>sb</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Southernmost of the Solomon Islands, Rennell and Bellona Province</location>
    <state>Solomon Islands</state>
    <site>East Rennell</site>
    <description>East Rennell makes up the southern third of Rennell Island, the southernmost island in the Solomon Island group in the western Pacific. Rennell, 86 km long x 15 km wide, is the largest raised coral atoll in the world. The site includes approximately 37,000 ha and a marine area extending 3 nautical miles to sea. A major feature of the island is Lake Tegano, which was the former lagoon on the atoll. The lake, the largest in the insular Pacific (15,500 ha), is brackish and contains many rugged limestone islands and endemic species. Rennell is mostly covered with dense forest, with a canopy averaging 20 m in height. Combined with the strong climatic effects of frequent cyclones, the site is a true natural laboratory for scientific study. The site is under customary land ownership and management.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="421" unique="487" trans="0" lat="-39.29083333" long="175.56222220">
    <criteria>(vi)(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1990</inscribeDate>
    <code>nz</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Tongariro and Wanganui Regions, North Island</location>
    <state>New Zealand</state>
    <site>Tongariro National Park</site>
    <description>In 1993 Tongariro became the first property to be inscribed on the World Heritage List under the revised criteria describing cultural landscapes. The mountains at the heart of the park have cultural and religious significance for the Maori people and symbolize the spiritual links between this community and its environment. The park has active and extinct volcanoes, a diverse range of ecosystems and some spectacular landscapes.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="677" unique="801" trans="0" lat="14.59000000" long="120.97000000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>ph</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Immaculate Conception: District of Intramuros, City of Manila Nuestra Senora: Municipality of Santa Maria, Province of Ilocos Sur San Agustin: Municipality of Paoay, Province of Ilocos Norte Santo Tomas: Municipality of Miag-ao, Province of Iloilo</location>
    <state>Philippines</state>
    <site>Baroque Churches of the Philippines</site>
    <description>These four churches, the first of which was built by the Spanish in the late 16th century, are located in Manila, Santa Maria, Paoay and Miag-ao. Their unique architectural style is a reinterpretation of European Baroque by Chinese and Philippine craftsmen.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="722" unique="853" trans="0" lat="16.93389000" long="121.13667000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>ph</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Ifugao Province, Cordillera Region, Luzon Island</location>
    <state>Philippines</state>
    <site>Rice Terraces of the Philippine Cordilleras</site>
    <description>For 2,000 years, the high rice fields of the Ifugao have followed the contours of the mountains. The fruit of knowledge handed down from one generation to the next, and the expression of sacred traditions and a delicate social balance, they have helped to create a landscape of great beauty that expresses the harmony between humankind and the environment.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1012" unique="1182" trans="0" lat="6.25000000" long="116.50000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>my</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>State of Sabah</location>
    <state>Malaysia</state>
    <site>Kinabalu Park</site>
    <description>Kinabalu Park, in the State of Sabah on the northern end of the island of Borneo, is dominated by Mount Kinabalu (4,095 m), the highest mountain between the Himalayas and New Guinea. It has a very wide range of habitats, from rich tropical lowland and hill rainforest to tropical mountain forest, sub-alpine forest and scrub on the higher elevations. It has been designated as a Centre of Plant Diversity for Southeast Asia and is exceptionally rich in species with examples of flora from the Himalayas, China, Australia, Malaysia, as well as pan-tropical flora.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="609" unique="723" trans="0" lat="-8.54333000" long="119.48944000">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>id</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>East Nusa Tenggara Province</location>
    <state>Indonesia</state>
    <site>Komodo National Park</site>
    <description>These volcanic islands are inhabited by a population of around 5,700 giant lizards, whose appearance and aggressive behaviour have led to them being called 'Komodo dragons'. They exist nowhere else in the world and are of great interest to scientists studying the theory of evolution. The rugged hillsides of dry savannah and pockets of thorny green vegetation contrast starkly with the brilliant white sandy beaches and the blue waters surging over coral.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="642" unique="762" trans="0" lat="-7.75222000" long="110.49167000">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>id</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Province of Central Java</location>
    <state>Indonesia</state>
    <site>Prambanan Temple Compounds</site>
    <description>Built in the 10th century, this is the largest temple compound dedicated to Shiva in Indonesia. Rising above the centre of the last of these concentric squares are three temples decorated with reliefs illustrating the epic of the &lt;I&gt;Ramayana&lt;/i&gt;, dedicated to the three great Hindu divinities (Shiva, Vishnu and Brahma) and three temples dedicated to the animals who serve them.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="955" unique="1118" trans="0" lat="-4.75000000" long="137.83333000">
    <criteria>(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>id</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Province of Papua (formerly Irian Jaya)</location>
    <state>Indonesia</state>
    <site>Lorentz National Park</site>
    <description>Lorentz National Park (2.5 million ha) is the largest protected area in South-East Asia. It is the only protected area in the world to incorporate a continuous, intact transect from snowcap to tropical marine environment, including extensive lowland wetlands. Located at the meeting-point of two colliding continental plates, the area has a complex geology with ongoing mountain formation as well as major sculpting by glaciation. The area also contains fossil sites which provide evidence of the evolution of life on New Guinea, a high level of endemism and the highest level of biodiversity in the region.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1167" unique="1344" trans="0" lat="-2.50000000" long="101.50000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>id</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Provinces of Nanggroe Aceh Darussalam, Sumatra Utara (North Sumatra), Jambi, Sumatra Barat (West Sumatra), Sumatra Selatan (South Sumatra), Bengkulu, and Lampung on the Island of Sumatra</location>
    <state>Indonesia</state>
    <site>Tropical Rainforest Heritage of Sumatra</site>
    <description>The 2.5 million hectare Tropical Rainforest Heritage of Sumatra site comprises three national parks: Gunung Leuser National Park, Kerinci Seblat National Park and Bukit Barisan Selatan National Park. The site holds the greatest potential for long-term conservation of the distinctive and diverse biota of Sumatra, including many endangered species. The protected area is home to an estimated 10,000 plant species, including 17 endemic genera; more than 200 mammal species; and some 580 bird species of which 465 are resident and 21 are endemic. Of the mammal species, 22 are Asian, not found elsewhere in the archipelago and 15 are confined to the Indonesian region, including the endemic Sumatran orang-utan. The site also provides biogeographic evidence of the evolution of the island.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="551" unique="648" trans="0" lat="-45.03602778" long="167.31961110">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1990</inscribeDate>
    <code>nz</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Southwest of South Island</location>
    <state>New Zealand</state>
    <site>Te Wahipounamu – South West New Zealand</site>
    <description>The landscape in this park, situated in south-west New Zealand, has been shaped by successive glaciations into fjords, rocky coasts, towering cliffs, lakes and waterfalls. Two-thirds of the park is covered with southern beech and podocarps, some of which are over 800 years old. The kea, the only alpine parrot in the world, lives in the park, as does the rare and endangered takahe, a large flightless bird.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="877" unique="1029" trans="0" lat="-50.75000000" long="166.10444440">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>nz</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>New Zealand Subantartic zone</location>
    <state>New Zealand</state>
    <site>New Zealand Sub-Antarctic Islands</site>
    <description>The New Zealand Sub-Antarctic Islands consist of five island groups (the Snares, Bounty Islands, Antipodes Islands, Auckland Islands and Campbell Island) in the Southern Ocean south-east of New Zealand. The islands, lying between the Antarctic and Subtropical Convergences and the seas, have a high level of productivity, biodiversity, wildlife population densities and endemism among birds, plants and invertebrates. They are particularly notable for the large number and diversity of pelagic seabirds and penguins that nest there. There are 126 bird species in total, including 40 seabirds of which five breed nowhere else in the world.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="592" unique="700" trans="0" lat="-7.60778000" long="110.20361000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>id</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Regency of Magelang, Province of Central Java</location>
    <state>Indonesia</state>
    <site>Borobudur Temple Compounds</site>
    <description>This famous Buddhist temple, dating from the 8th and 9th centuries, is located in central Java. It was built in three tiers: a pyramidal base with five concentric square terraces, the trunk of a cone with three circular platforms and, at the top, a monumental stupa. The walls and balustrades are decorated with fine low reliefs, covering a total surface area of 2,500 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Around the circular platforms are 72 openwork stupas, each containing a statue of the Buddha. The monument was restored with UNESCO's help in the 1970s.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="593" unique="701" trans="0" lat="-7.40000000" long="110.81666670">
    <criteria>(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>id</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Province of Central Java</location>
    <state>Indonesia</state>
    <site>Sangiran Early Man Site</site>
    <description>Excavations here from 1936 to 1941 led to the discovery of the first hominid fossil at this site. Later, 50 fossils of &lt;I&gt;Meganthropus palaeo&lt;/I&gt; and &lt;I&gt;Pithecanthropus erectus/Homo erectus&lt;/I&gt; were found – half of all the world's known hominid fossils. Inhabited for the past one and a half million years, Sangiran is one of the key sites for the understanding of human evolution.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="147" unique="163" trans="0" lat="-12.83333333" long="132.83333330">
    <criteria>(i)(vi)(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Northern territory</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Kakadu National Park</site>
    <description>This unique archaeological and ethnological reserve, located in the Northern Territory, has been inhabited continuously for more than 40,000 years. The cave paintings, rock carvings and archaeological sites record the skills and way of life of the region’s inhabitants, from the hunter-gatherers of prehistoric times to the Aboriginal people still living there. It is a unique example of a complex of ecosystems, including tidal flats, floodplains, lowlands and plateaux, and provides a habitat for a wide range of rare or endemic species of plants and animals.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="154" unique="172" trans="0" lat="-18.28611111" long="147.70000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Off the east coast of the Queensland mainland</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Great Barrier Reef</site>
    <description>The Great Barrier Reef is a site of remarkable variety and beauty on the north-east coast of Australia. It contains the world’s largest collection of coral reefs, with 400 types of coral, 1,500 species of fish and 4,000 types of mollusc. It also holds great scientific interest as the habitat of species such as the dugong (‘sea cow’) and the large green turtle, which are threatened with extinction.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="167" unique="185" trans="0" lat="-34.00000000" long="143.00000000">
    <criteria>(iii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Balranald and Wentworth shires, New South Wales</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Willandra Lakes Region</site>
    <description>The fossil remains of a series of lakes and sand formations that date from the Pleistocene can be found in this region, together with archaeological evidence of human occupation dating from 45–60,000 years ago. It is a unique landmark in the study of human evolution on the Australian continent. Several well-preserved fossils of giant marsupials have also been found here.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="181" unique="201" trans="0" lat="-41.58333333" long="145.41666670">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(vi)(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>State of Tasmania</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Tasmanian Wilderness</site>
    <description>In a region that has been subjected to severe glaciation, these parks and reserves, with their steep gorges, covering an area of over 1 million ha, constitute one of the last expanses of temperate rainforest in the world. Remains found in limestone caves attest to the human occupation of the area for more than 20,000 years.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="186" unique="206" trans="0" lat="-31.56555556" long="159.08833330">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>New South Wales</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Lord Howe Island Group</site>
    <description>A remarkable example of isolated oceanic islands, born of volcanic activity more than 2,000 m under the sea, these islands boast a spectacular topography and are home to numerous endemic species, especially birds.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="917" unique="1071" trans="0" lat="-33.70000000" long="150.00000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location />
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Greater Blue Mountains Area</site>
    <description>The Greater Blue Mountains Area consists of 1.03 million ha of sandstone plateaux, escarpments and gorges dominated by temperate eucalypt forest.  The site, comprised of eight protected areas, is noted for its representation of the evolutionary adaptation and diversification of the eucalypts in post-Gondwana isolation on the Australian continent.  Ninety-one eucalypt taxa occur within the Greater Blue Mountains Area which is also outstanding for its exceptional expression of the structural and ecological diversity of the eucalypts associated with its wide range of habitats.  The site provides significant representation of Australia's biodiversity with ten percent of the vascular flora as well as significant numbers of rare or threatened species, including endemic and evolutionary relict species, such as the Wollemi pine, which have persisted in highly-restricted microsites.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1094" unique="1272" trans="0" lat="-17.50000000" long="128.50000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Western Australia</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Purnululu National Park</site>
    <description>The 239,723 ha Purnululu National Park is located in the State of Western Australia. It contains the deeply dissected Bungle Bungle Range composed of Devonian-age quartz sandstone eroded over a period of 20 million years into a series of beehive-shaped towers or cones, whose steeply sloping surfaces are distinctly marked by regular horizontal bands of dark-grey cyanobacterial crust (single-celled photosynthetic organisms). These outstanding examples of cone karst owe their existence and uniqueness to several interacting geological, biological, erosional and climatic phenomena.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1131" unique="1311" trans="0" lat="-37.80611111" long="144.97027780">
    <criteria>(ii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Melbourne, Victoria</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Royal Exhibition Building and Carlton Gardens</site>
    <description>The Royal Exhibition Building and its surrounding Carlton Gardens were designed for the great international exhibitions of 1880 and 1888 in Melbourne. The building and grounds were designed by Joseph Reed. The building is constructed of brick and timber, steel and slate. It combines elements from the Byzantine, Romanesque, Lombardic and Italian Renaissance styles. The property is typical of the international exhibition movement which saw over 50 exhibitions staged between 1851 and 1915 in venues including Paris, New York, Vienna, Calcutta, Kingston (Jamaica) and Santiago (Chile). All shared a common theme and aims: to chart material and moral progress through displays of industry from all nations.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="368" unique="422" trans="0" lat="-28.25000000" long="150.05000000">
    <criteria>(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1986</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>States of New South Wales and Queensland</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Gondwana Rainforests of Australia</site>
    <description>This site, comprising several protected areas, is situated predominantly along the Great Escarpment on Australia’s east coast. The outstanding geological features displayed around shield volcanic craters and the high number of rare and threatened rainforest species are of international significance for science and conservation.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="447" unique="519" trans="0" lat="-25.33333333" long="131.00000000">
    <criteria>(v)(vi)(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Northern territory</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Ulu&lt;U&gt;r&lt;/U&gt;u-Kata Tju&lt;U&gt;t&lt;/U&gt;a National Park</site>
    <description>This park, formerly called Uluru (Ayers Rock – Mount Olga) National Park, features spectacular geological formations that dominate the vast red sandy plain of central Australia. Uluru, an immense monolith, and Kata Tjuta, the rock domes located west of Uluru, form part of the traditional belief system of one of the oldest human societies in the world. The traditional owners of Uluru-Kata Tjuta are the Anangu Aboriginal people.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="486" unique="565" trans="0" lat="-15.65000000" long="144.96666670">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>State of Queensland</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Wet Tropics of Queensland</site>
    <description>This area, which stretches along the north-east coast of Australia for some 450 km, is made up largely of tropical rainforests. This biotope offers a particularly extensive and varied array of plants, as well as marsupials and singing birds, along with other rare and endangered animals and plant species.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="577" unique="683" trans="0" lat="-53.10000000" long="73.50000000">
    <criteria>(viii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>Territory of Heard Island and McDonald Islands</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Heard and McDonald Islands</site>
    <description>Heard Island and McDonald Islands are located in the Southern Ocean, approximately 1,700 km from the Antarctic continent and 4,100 km south-west of Perth. As the only volcanically active subantarctic islands they ‘open a window into the earth’, thus providing the opportunity to observe ongoing geomorphic processes and glacial dynamics. The distinctive conservation value of Heard and McDonald – one of the world’s rare pristine island ecosystems – lies in the complete absence of alien plants and animals, as well as human impact.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="578" unique="684" trans="0" lat="-25.48611111" long="113.43611110">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>State of Western Australia</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Shark Bay, Western Australia</site>
    <description>At the most westerly point of the Australian continent, Shark Bay, with its islands and the land surrounding it, has three exceptional natural features: its vast sea-grass beds, which are the largest (4,800 km2) and richest in the world; its dugong (‘sea cow’) population; and its stromatolites (colonies of algae which form hard, dome-shaped deposits and are among the oldest forms of life on earth). Shark Bay is also home to five species of endangered mammals.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="629" unique="747" trans="0" lat="-54.59472222" long="158.89555560">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>State of Tasmania</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Macquarie Island</site>
    <description>Macquarie Island (34 km long x 5 km wide) is an oceanic island in the Southern Ocean, lying 1,500 km south-east of Tasmania and approximately halfway between Australia and the Antarctic continent. The island is the exposed crest of the undersea Macquarie Ridge, raised to its present position where the Indo-Australian tectonic plate meets the Pacific plate. It is a site of major geoconservation significance, being the only place on earth where rocks from the earth’s mantle (6 km below the ocean floor) are being actively exposed above sea-level. These unique exposures include excellent examples of pillow basalts and other extrusive rocks.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="630" unique="748" trans="0" lat="-25.21666667" long="153.13333330">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>au</code>
    <region>Pacific</region>
    <location>State of Queensland</location>
    <state>Australia</state>
    <site>Fraser Island</site>
    <description>Fraser Island lies just off the east coast of Australia. At 122 km long, it is the largest sand island in the world. Majestic remnants of tall rainforest growing on sand and half the world’s perched freshwater dune lakes are found inland from the beach. The combination of shifting sand-dunes, tropical rainforests and lakes makes it an exceptional site.</description>
  </row>
  </worldheritage>