<worldheritage promo="UNESCO">
<row id="1161" unique="1341" trans="0" lat="13.80708333" long="-61.07036111">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>lc</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>near the town of Soufriere, southwestern region of St Lucia</location>
    <state>Saint Lucia</state>
    <site>Pitons Management Area</site>
    <description>The 2,909-ha site near the town of Soufriere includes the Pitons, two volcanic spires rising side by side from the sea (770 m and 743 m high respectively), linked by the Piton Mitan ridge. The volcanic complex includes a geothermal field with sulphurous fumeroles and hot springs. Coral reefs cover almost 60% of the site’s marine area. A survey has revealed 168 species of finfish, 60 species of cnidaria, including corals, eight molluscs, 14 sponges, 11 echinoderms, 15 arthropods and eight annelid worms. The dominant terrestrial vegetation is tropical moist forest grading to subtropical wet forest, with small areas of dry forest and wet elfin woodland on the summits. At least 148 plant species have been recorded on Gros Piton, 97 on Petit Piton and the intervening ridge, among them eight rare tree species. The Gros Piton is home to some 27 bird species (five of them endemic), three indigenous rodents, one opossum, three bats, eight reptiles and three amphibians.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="910" unique="1063" trans="0" lat="17.34694000" long="-62.83722000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>kn</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Parish of St Thomas, St Christopher (St Kitts)</location>
    <state>Saint Kitts and Nevis</state>
    <site>Brimstone Hill Fortress National Park</site>
    <description>Brimstone Hill Fortress National Park is an outstanding, well-preserved example of 17th- and 18th-century military architecture in a Caribbean context. Designed by the British and built by African slave labour, the fortress is testimony to European colonial expansion, the African slave trade and the emergence of new societies in the Caribbean.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="204" unique="225" trans="0" lat="23.13333333" long="-82.35000000">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Province of Ciudad de la Habana</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>Old Havana and its Fortifications</site>
    <description>Havana was founded in 1519 by the Spanish. By the 17th century, it had become one of the Caribbean's main centres for ship-building. Although it is today a sprawling metropolis of 2 million inhabitants, its old centre retains an interesting mix of Baroque and neoclassical monuments, and a homogeneous ensemble of private houses with arcades, balconies, wrought-iron gates and internal courtyards.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="460" unique="535" trans="0" lat="21.80305556" long="-79.98444444">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Province of Sancti Spiritus</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>Trinidad and the Valley de los Ingenios</site>
    <description>Founded in the early 16th century in honour of the Holy Trinity, the city was a bridgehead for the conquest of the American continent. Its 18th- and 19th-century buildings, such as the Palacio Brunet and the Palacio Cantero, were built in its days of prosperity from the sugar trade.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="839" unique="989" trans="0" lat="20.45000000" long="-75.00000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2001</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Guantánamo and Holguín Provinces</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>Alejandro de Humboldt National Park</site>
    <description>Complex geology and varied topography have given rise to a diversity of ecosystems and species unmatched in the insular Caribbean and created one of the most biologically diverse tropical island sites on earth. Many of the underlying rocks are toxic to plants so species have had to adapt to survive in these hostile conditions. This unique process of evolution has resulted in the development of many new species and the park is one of the most important sites in the Western Hemisphere for the conservation of endemic flora. Endemism of vertebrates and invertebrates is also very high.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="840" unique="991" trans="0" lat="22.61667000" long="-83.71667000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Province of Pinar del Rio</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>Viñales Valley</site>
    <description>The Viñales valley is encircled by mountains and its landscape is interspersed with dramatic rocky outcrops. Traditional techniques are still in use for agricultural production, particularly of tobacco. The quality of this cultural landscape is enhanced by the vernacular architecture of its farms and villages, where a rich multi-ethnic society survives, illustrating the cultural development of the islands of the Caribbean, and of Cuba.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="841" unique="992" trans="0" lat="19.96666667" long="-75.87083333">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Provincia de Santiago de Cuba</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>San Pedro de la Roca Castle, Santiago de Cuba</site>
    <description>Commercial and political rivalries in the Caribbean region in the 17th century resulted in the construction of this massive series of fortifications on a rocky promontory, built to protect the important port of Santiago. This intricate complex of forts, magazines, bastions and batteries is the most complete, best-preserved example of Spanish-American military architecture, based on Italian and Renaissance design principles.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="180" unique="199" trans="0" lat="19.57361000" long="-72.24417000">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>ht</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Département du Nord</location>
    <state>Haiti</state>
    <site>National History Park – Citadel, Sans Souci, Ramiers</site>
    <description>These Haitian monuments date from the beginning of the 19th century, when Haiti proclaimed its independence. The Palace of Sans Souci, the buildings at Ramiers and, in particular, the Citadel serve as universal symbols of liberty, being the first monuments to be constructed by black slaves who had gained their freedom.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="889" unique="1041" trans="0" lat="19.88333000" long="-77.63333000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Desembarco del Granma National Park, south-east corner of the the Republic of Cuba</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>Desembarco del Granma National Park</site>
    <description>Desembarco del Granma National Park, with its uplifted marine terraces and associated ongoing development of karst topography and features, represents a globally significant example of geomorphologic and physiographic features and ongoing geological processes. The area, which is situated in and around Cabo Cruz in south-east Cuba, includes spectacular terraces and cliffs, as well as some of the most pristine and impressive coastal cliffs bordering the western Atlantic.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1008" unique="1178" trans="0" lat="20.03000000" long="-75.39138889">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Santiago and Guantanamo Provinces, South-Eastern Region</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>Archaeological Landscape of the First Coffee Plantations in the South-East of Cuba</site>
    <description>The remains of the 19th-century coffee plantations in the foothills of the Sierra Maestra are unique evidence of a pioneer form of agriculture in a difficult terrain. They throw considerable light on the economic, social, and technological history of the Caribbean and Latin American region.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1202" unique="1379" trans="0" lat="22.14722000" long="-80.45278000">
    <criteria>(ii)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>cu</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Municipality of Cienfuegos</location>
    <state>Cuba</state>
    <site>Urban Historic Centre of Cienfuegos</site>
    <description>The colonial town of Cienfuegos was founded in 1819 in the Spanish territory but was initially settled by immigrants of French origin. It became a trading place for sugar cane, tobacco and coffee. Situated on the Caribbean coast of southern-central Cuba at the heart of the country’s sugar cane, mango, tobacco and coffee production area, the town first developed in the neoclassical style. It later became more eclectic but retained a harmonious overall townscape. Among buildings of particular interest are the Government Palace (City Hall), San Lorenzo School, the Bishopric, the Ferrer Palace, the former lyceum, and some residential houses. Cienfuegos is the first, and an outstanding example of an architectural ensemble representing the new ideas of modernity, hygiene and order in urban planning as developed in Latin America from the 19th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="814" unique="962" trans="0" lat="15.26666667" long="-61.28333333">
    <criteria>(viii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>dm</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>South central part of the island</location>
    <state>Dominica</state>
    <site>Morne Trois Pitons National Park</site>
    <description>Luxuriant natural tropical forest blends with scenic volcanic features of great scientific interest in this national park centred on the 1,342-m-high volcano known as Morne Trois Pitons. With its precipitous slopes and deeply incised valleys, 50 fumaroles, hot springs, three freshwater lakes, a &amp;#39;boiling lake&amp;#39; and five volcanoes, located on the park&amp;#39;s nearly 7,000 ha, together with the richest biodiversity in the Lesser Antilles, Morne Trois Pitons National Park presents a rare combination of natural features of World Heritage value.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="526" unique="615" trans="0" lat="18.48333333" long="-69.91666667">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1990</inscribeDate>
    <code>do</code>
    <region>Caribbean</region>
    <location>Distrito Nacional</location>
    <state>Dominican Republic</state>
    <site>Colonial City of Santo Domingo</site>
    <description>After Christopher Columbus's arrival on the island in 1492, Santo Domingo became the site of the first cathedral, hospital, customs house and university in the Americas. This colonial town, founded in 1498, was laid out on a grid pattern that became the model for almost all town planners in the New World.</description>
  </row>
  </worldheritage>