<worldheritage promo="UNESCO">
  <row id="334" unique="380" trans="0" lat="-20.49972222" long="-43.85777778">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Minas Gerais, City of Congohas</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Sanctuary of Bom Jesus do Congonhas</site>
    <description>This sanctuary in Minais Gerais, south of Belo Horizonte was built in the second half of the 18th century. It consists of a church with a magnificent Rococo interior of Italian inspiration; an outdoor stairway decorated with statues of the prophets; and seven chapels illustrating the Stations of the Cross, in which the polychrome sculptures by Aleijadinho are masterpieces of a highly original, moving, expressive form of Baroque art.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="971" unique="1135" trans="0" lat="-42.50000000" long="-73.76666667">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>cl</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Municipalities of Castro, Chonchi, Dalcahue, Puqueldón, Quemchi, and Quinchao, Chiloé Province, X Region de los Lagos</location>
    <state>Chile</state>
    <site>Churches of Chiloé</site>
    <description>The Churches of Chiloé represent a unique example in Latin America of an outstanding form of ecclesiastical wooden architecture. They represent a tradition initiated by the Jesuit Peripatetic Mission in the 17th and 18th centuries, continued and enriched by the Franciscans during the 19th century and still prevailing today. These churches embody the intangible richness of the Chiloé Archipelago, and bear witness to a successful fusion of indigenous and European culture, the full integration of its architecture in the landscape and environment, as well as to the spiritual values of the communities.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1216" unique="1393" trans="0" lat="3.96666667" long="-81.61666667">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2006</inscribeDate>
    <code>co</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Valle del Cauca Region</location>
    <state>Colombia</state>
    <site>Malpelo Fauna and Flora Sanctuary</site>
    <description>Located some 506 km off the coast of Colombia, the site includes Malpelo island (350 ha) and the surrounding marine environment (857,150 ha). This vast marine park, the largest no-fishing zone in the Eastern Tropical Pacific, provides a critical habitat for internationally threatened marine species, and is a major source of nutrients resulting in large aggregations of marine biodiversity. It is in particular a ‘reservoir&amp;#39; for sharks, giant grouper and billfish and is one of the few places in the world where sightings of the short-nosed ragged-toothed shark, a deepwater shark, have been confirmed. Widely recognized as one of the top diving sites in the world, due to the presence of steep walls and caves of outstanding natural beauty, these deep waters support important populations of large predators and pelagic species (e.g. aggregations of over 200 hammerhead sharks and over 1,000 silky sharks, whale sharks and tuna have been recorded) in an undisturbed environment where they maintain natural behavioural patterns.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1" unique="4" trans="0" lat="-0.81667000" long="-91.00000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1978</inscribeDate>
    <code>ec</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Cantons: San Cristobal, Santa Cruz and Isabela, Province of Galapagos</location>
    <state>Ecuador</state>
    <site>Galápagos Islands</site>
    <description>Situated in the Pacific Ocean some 1,000 km from the South American continent, these 19 islands and the surrounding marine reserve have been called a unique ‘living museum and showcase of evolution’. Located at the confluence of three ocean currents, the Galápagos are a ‘melting pot’ of marine species Ongoing seismic and volcanic activity reflects the processes that formed the islands. These processes, together with the extreme isolation of the islands, led to the development of unusual animal life – such as the land iguana, the giant tortoise and the many types of finch – that inspired Charles Darwin’s theory of evolution following his visit in 1835.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="149" unique="167" trans="0" lat="15.27059000" long="-89.04025000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>gt</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of Izabal</location>
    <state>Guatemala</state>
    <site>Archaeological Park and Ruins of Quirigua</site>
    <description>Inhabited since the 2nd century A.D., Quirigua had become during the reign of Cauac Sky (723–84) the capital of an autonomous and prosperous state.  The ruins of Quirigua contain some outstanding 8th-century monuments and an impressive series of carved stelae and sculpted calendars that constitute an essential source for the study of Mayan civilization.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="631" unique="749" trans="0" lat="20.47639000" long="-97.37750000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Etat de Veracruz, municipalité de Papantla</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>El Tajin, Pre-Hispanic City</site>
    <description>Located in the state of Veracruz, El Tajin was at its height from the early 9th to the early 13th century. It became the most important centre in north-east Mesoamerica after the fall of the Teotihuacan Empire. Its cultural influence extended all along the Gulf and penetrated into the Maya region and the high plateaux of central Mexico. Its architecture, which is unique in Mesoamerica, is characterized by elaborate carved reliefs on the columns and frieze. The 'Pyramid of the Niches', a masterpiece of ancient Mexican and American architecture, reveals the astronomical and symbolic significance of the buildings. El Tajin has survived as an outstanding example of the grandeur and importance of the pre-Hispanic cultures of Mexico.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="815" unique="963" trans="0" lat="20.67388889" long="-103.33972220">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Jalisco, Guadalajara</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Hospicio Cabañas, Guadalajara</site>
    <description>The Hospicio Cabañas was built at the beginning of the 19th century to provide care and shelter for the disadvantaged – orphans, old people, the handicapped and chronic invalids. This remarkable complex, which incorporates several unusual features designed specifically to meet the needs of its occupants, was unique for its time. It is also notable for the harmonious relationship between the open and built spaces, the simplicity of its design, and its size. In the early 20th century, the chapel was decorated with a superb series of murals, now considered some of the masterpieces of Mexican art. They are the work of José Clemente Orozco, one of the greatest Mexican muralists of the period.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1209" unique="1386" trans="0" lat="20.86305556" long="-103.77861111">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(v)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2006</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Valles Region, Jalisco State</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Agave Landscape and Ancient Industrial Facilities of Tequila</site>
    <description>The 34,658 ha site, between the foothills of the Tequila Volcano and the deep valley of the Rio Grande River, is part of an expansive landscape of blue agave, shaped by the culture of the plant used since the 16th century to produce tequila spirit and for at least 2,000 years to make fermented drinks and cloth. Within the landscape are working distilleries reflecting the growth in the international consumption of tequila in the 19th and 20th centuries. Today, the agave culture is seen as part of national identity. The area encloses a living, working landscape of blue agave fields and the urban settlements of Tequila, Arenal, and Amatitan with large distilleries where the agave ‘pineapple' is fermented and distilled. The property is also a testimony to the Teuchitlan cultures which shaped the Tequila area from AD 200-900, notably through the creation of terraces for agriculture, housing, temples, ceremonial mounds and ball courts.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="500" unique="583" trans="0" lat="-12.05139000" long="-77.04306000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>City of Lima</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Lima</site>
    <description>Although severely damaged by earthquakes, this 'City of the Kings' was, until the middle of the 18th century, the capital and most important city of the Spanish dominions in South America. Many of its buildings, such as the Convent of San Francisco (the largest of its type in this part of the world), are the result of collaboration between local craftspeople and others from the Old World.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1138" unique="1319" trans="0" lat="7.43300000" long="-81.76600000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>pa</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Provinces of Veraguas and Chiriquí</location>
    <state>Panama</state>
    <site>Coiba National Park and its Special Zone of Marine Protection</site>
    <description>Coiba National Park, off the southwest coast of Panama, protects Coiba Island, 38 smaller islands and the surrounding marine areas within the Gulf of Chiriqui. Protected from the cold winds and effects of El Niño, Coiba’s Pacific tropical moist forest maintains exceptionally high levels of endemism of mammals, birds and plants due to the ongoing evolution of new species. It is also the last refuge for a number of threatened animals such as the crested eagle. The property is an outstanding natural laboratory for scientific research and provides a key ecological link to the Tropical Eastern Pacific for the transit and survival of pelagic fish and marine mammals.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="548" unique="644" trans="0" lat="-7.75000000" long="-77.25000000">
    <criteria>(iii)(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1990</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of San Martin, Province Mariscal Caceres, District of Huicungo</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Río Abiseo National Park</site>
    <description>The park was created in 1983 to protect the fauna and flora of the rainforests that are characteristic of this region of the Andes. There is a high level of endemism among the fauna and flora found in the park. The yellow-tailed woolly monkey, previously thought extinct, is found only in this area. Research undertaken since 1985 has already uncovered 36 previously unknown archaeological sites at altitudes of between 2,500 and 4,000 m, which give a good picture of pre-Inca society.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="700" unique="828" trans="0" lat="-14.72583000" long="-75.14861000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Libertadores / Wari Region</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Lines and Geoglyphs of Nasca and Pampas de Jumana</site>
    <description>Located in the arid Peruvian coastal plain, some 400 km south of Lima, the geoglyphs of Nasca and the pampas of Jumana cover about 450 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. These lines, which were scratched on the surface of the ground between 500 B.C. and A.D. 500, are among archaeology's greatest enigmas because of their quantity, nature, size and continuity. The geoglyphs depict living creatures, stylized plants and imaginary beings, as well as geometric figures several kilometres long. They are believed to have had ritual astronomical functions.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1016" unique="1186" trans="0" lat="-16.40000000" long="-71.53333333">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Arequipa</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Historical Centre of the City of Arequipa</site>
    <description>The historic centre of Arequipa, built in volcanic sillar rock, represents an integration of European and native building techniques and characteristics, expressed in the admirable work of colonial masters and Criollo and Indian masons. This combination of influences is illustrated by the city's robust walls, archways and vaults, courtyards and open spaces, and the intricate Baroque decoration of its facades.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="410" unique="473" trans="0" lat="19.38333000" long="-87.79167000">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Quintana Roo, Cozumel et Felipe Carrillo Puerto</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Sian Ka'an</site>
    <description>In the language of the Mayan peoples who once inhabited this region, Sian Ka'an means 'Origin of the Sky'. Located on the east coast of the Yucatán peninsula, this biosphere reserve contains tropical forests, mangroves and marshes, as well as a large marine section intersected by a barrier reef. It provides a habitat for a remarkably rich flora and a fauna comprising more than 300 species of birds, as well as a large number of the region's characteristic terrestrial vertebrates, which cohabit in the diverse environment formed by its complex hydrological system.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="411" unique="474" trans="0" lat="17.48333000" long="-92.05000000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Chiapas, Municipality of Palenque</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Pre-Hispanic City and National Park of Palenque</site>
    <description>A prime example of a Mayan sanctuary of the classical period, Palenque was at its height between AD 500 and 700, when its influence extended throughout the basin of the Usumacinta River. The elegance and craftsmanship of the buildings, as well as the lightness of the sculpted reliefs with their Mayan mythological themes, attest to the creative genius of this civilization.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="412" unique="475" trans="0" lat="19.41833000" long="-99.13278000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>District Federal.  Delegations: Cuauhtemoc, Venustiano Carranza et Xochimilco</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Mexico City and Xochimilco</site>
    <description>Built in the 16th century by the Spanish on the ruins of Tenochtitlan, the old Aztec capital, Mexico City is now one of the world's largest and most densely populated cities. It has five Aztec temples, the ruins of which have been identified, a cathedral (the largest on the continent) and some fine 19th- and 20th-century public buildings such as the Palacio de las Bellas Artes. Xochimilco lies 28 km south of Mexico City. With its network of canals and artificial islands, it testifies to the efforts of the Aztec people to build a habitat in the midst of an unfavourable environment. Its characteristic urban and rural structures, built since the 16th century and during the colonial period; have been preserved in an exceptional manner.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="414" unique="477" trans="0" lat="19.69167000" long="-98.84167000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Municipalities of Teotihuacan De Arista and San Martin De Las Piramides</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Pre-Hispanic City of Teotihuacan</site>
    <description>The holy city of Teotihuacan ('the place where the gods were created') is situated some 50 km north-east of Mexico City. Built between the 1st and 7th centuries A.D., it is characterized by the vast size of its monuments – in particular, the Temple of Quetzalcoatl and the Pyramids of the Sun and the Moon, laid out on geometric and symbolic principles. As one of the most powerful cultural centres in Mesoamerica, Teotihuacan extended its cultural and artistic influence throughout the region, and even beyond.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="415" unique="478" trans="0" lat="17.06194000" long="-96.72167000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Etat de Oaxaca de Juarez, municipalites de Oaxaca, Xoxocotlan et Cuilapan</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Oaxaca and Archaeological Site of Monte Albán</site>
    <description>Inhabited over a period of 1,500 years by a succession of peoples – Olmecs, Zapotecs and Mixtecs – the terraces, dams, canals, pyramids and artificial mounds of Monte Albán were literally carved out of the mountain and are the symbols of a sacred topography. The nearby city of Oaxaca, which is built on a grid pattern, is a good example of Spanish colonial town planning. The solidity and volume of the city's buildings show that they were adapted to the earthquake-prone region in which these architectural gems were constructed.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="135" unique="148" trans="0" lat="9.55388889" long="-79.65583333">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1980</inscribeDate>
    <code>pa</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Colon - Distric of Cristobal</location>
    <state>Panama</state>
    <site>Fortifications on the Caribbean Side of Panama: Portobelo-San Lorenzo</site>
    <description>Magnificent examples of 17th- and 18th-century military architecture, these Panamanian forts on the Caribbean coast form part of the defence system built by the Spanish Crown to protect transatlantic trade.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="159" unique="177" trans="0" lat="7.73611111" long="-77.54722222">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>pa</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Darien</location>
    <state>Panama</state>
    <site>Darien National Park</site>
    <description>Forming a bridge between the two continents of the New World, Darien National Park contains an exceptional variety of habitats – sandy beaches, rocky coasts, mangroves, swamps, and lowland and upland tropical forests containing remarkable wildlife. Two Indian tribes live in the park.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="790" unique="934" trans="0" lat="8.95111111" long="-79.54055556">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>pa</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Panama’ Province, Panama’ District</location>
    <state>Panama</state>
    <site>Archaeological Site of Panamá Viejo and Historic District of Panamá</site>
    <description>Founded in 1519 by the conquistador Pedrarías Dávila, Panamá Viejo is the oldest European settlement on the Pacific coast of the Americas. It was laid out on a rectilinear grid and marks the transference from Europe of the idea of a planned town. Abandoned in the mid-17th century, it was replaced by a ‘new town’ (the ‘Historic District’), which has also preserved its original street plan, its architecture and an unusual mixture of Spanish, French and early American styles. The Salón Bolívar was the venue for the unsuccessful attempt made by &lt;I&gt;El Libertador&lt;/I&gt; in 1826 to establish a multinational continental congress.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="648" unique="768" trans="0" lat="-27.13333000" long="-55.70000000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>py</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department d’Itapua, region Orientale</location>
    <state>Paraguay</state>
    <site>Jesuit Missions of La Santísima Trinidad de Paraná and Jesús de Tavarangue</site>
    <description>In addition to their artistic interest, these missions are a reminder of the Jesuits' Christianization of the Río de la Plata basin in the 17th and 18th centuries, with the accompanying social and economic initiatives.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="273" unique="304" trans="0" lat="-13.52222000" long="-71.98333000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>City of Cuzco</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>City of Cuzco</site>
    <description>Situated in the Peruvian Andes, Cuzco developed, under the Inca ruler Pachacutec, into a complex urban centre with distinct religious and administrative functions. It was surrounded by clearly delineated areas for agricultural, artisan and industrial production. When the Spaniards conquered it in the 16th century, they preserved the basic structure but built Baroque churches and palaces over the ruins of the Inca city.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="274" unique="305" trans="0" lat="-13.11666667" long="-72.58333333">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Left bank of the Vilcanota river, between its tributaries the Kusichaca and Aobamba rivers, in the department of Cuzco, Urubamba Province, District of Macchu Picchu</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Historic Sanctuary of Machu Picchu</site>
    <description>Machu Picchu stands 2,430 m above sea-level, in the middle of a tropical mountain forest, in an extraordinarily beautiful setting. It was probably the most amazing urban creation of the Inca Empire at its height; its giant walls, terraces and ramps seem as if they have been cut naturally in the continuous rock escarpments. The natural setting, on the eastern slopes of the Andes, encompasses the upper Amazon basin with its rich diversity of flora and fauna.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="330" unique="375" trans="0" lat="-9.59277254" long="-77.17845350">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Ancash Department, Huari Province, Chavin District</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Chavin (Archaeological Site)</site>
    <description>The archaeological site of Chavin gave its name to the culture that developed between 1500 and 300 B.C. in this high valley of the Peruvian Andes. This former place of worship is one of the earliest and best-known pre-Columbian sites. Its appearance is striking, with the complex of terraces and squares, surrounded by structures of dressed stone, and the mainly zoomorphic ornamentation.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="333" unique="379" trans="0" lat="-9.33333000" long="-77.40000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department Ancash, Provincia: recuay, Carhuas, Huaráz, Yungay, Pomabamba, Mariscal Luzuriaga, Huari, Corongo, Sihuas y Bolognesi</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Huascarán National Park</site>
    <description>Situated in the Cordillera Blanca, the world&amp;#39;s highest tropical mountain range, Mount Huascarán rises to 6,768 m above sea-level. The deep ravines watered by numerous torrents, the glacial lakes and the variety of the vegetation make it a site of spectacular beauty. It is the home of such species as the spectacled bear and the Andean condor.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="366" unique="419" trans="0" lat="-8.10000000" long="-79.08333000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1986</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Depart.: La Libertad.   Prov.: Trujillo.  Distr.: Huanchaco</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Chan Chan Archaeological Zone</site>
    <description>The Chimu Kingdom, with Chan Chan as its capital, reached its apogee in the 15th century, not long before falling to the Incas. The planning of this huge city, the largest in pre-Columbian America, reflects a strict political and social strategy, marked by the city&amp;#39;s division into nine &amp;#39;citadels&amp;#39; or &amp;#39;palaces&amp;#39; forming autonomous units.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="416" unique="479" trans="0" lat="19.04722000" long="-98.20833000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Etat de Puebla, municipalites de Puebla, San Pedro Cholula et San Andres Cholula</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Puebla</site>
    <description>Puebla, which was founded &lt;I&gt;ex nihilo&lt;/i&gt; in 1531, is situated about 100 km east of Mexico City, at the foot of the Popocatepetl volcano. It has preserved its great religious structures such as the 16th–17th-century cathedral and fine buildings like the old archbishop's palace, as well as a host of houses with walls covered in tiles (&lt;I&gt;azulejos&lt;/i&gt;). The new aesthetic concepts resulting from the fusion of European and American styles were adopted locally and are peculiar to the Baroque district of Puebla.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="482" unique="561" trans="0" lat="21.01694000" long="-101.25556000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Etat de: Guanajuato.   Municipalite:  Guanajuato</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Town of Guanajuato and Adjacent Mines</site>
    <description>Founded by the Spanish in the early 16th century, Guanajuato became the world's leading silver-extraction centre in the 18th century. This past can be seen in its 'subterranean streets' and the 'Boca del Inferno', a mineshaft that plunges a breathtaking 600 m. The town's fine Baroque and neoclassical buildings, resulting from the prosperity of the mines, have influenced buildings throughout central Mexico. The churches of La Compañía and La Valenciana are considered to be among the most beautiful examples of Baroque architecture in Central and South America. Guanajuato was also witness to events which changed the history of the country.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="483" unique="562" trans="0" lat="20.66667000" long="-88.60000000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Etat de Yucatan, Municipalité de Tinum</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Pre-Hispanic City of Chichen-Itza</site>
    <description>This sacred site was one of the greatest Mayan centres of the Yucatán peninsula. Throughout its nearly 1,000-year history, different peoples have left their mark on the city. The Maya and Toltec vision of the world and the universe is revealed in their stone monuments and artistic works. The fusion of Mayan construction techniques with new elements from central Mexico make Chichen-Itza one of the most important examples of the Mayan-Toltec civilization in Yucatán. Several buildings have survived, such as the Warriors’ Temple, El Castillo and the circular observatory known as El Caracol.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="554" unique="652" trans="0" lat="27.79222000" long="-114.22778000">
    <criteria>(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Basse Californie Sud, Municipality of Mulege</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Whale Sanctuary of El Vizcaino</site>
    <description>Located in the central part of the peninsula of Baja California, the sanctuary contains some exceptionally interesting ecosystems. The coastal lagoons of Ojo de Liebre and San Ignacio are important reproduction and wintering sites for the grey whale, harbour seal, California sea lion, northern elephant-seal and blue whale. The lagoons are also home to four species of the endangered marine turtle.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="560" unique="662" trans="0" lat="30.37583000" long="-107.95556000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Municipality of Casas Grandes, State of Chihuahua</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Archeological Zone of Paquimé, Casas Grandes</site>
    <description>Paquimé, Casas Grandes, which reached its apogee in the 14th and 15th centuries, played a key role in trade and cultural contacts between the Pueblo culture of the south-western United States and northern Mexico and the more advanced civilizations of Mesoamerica. The extensive remains, only part of which have been excavated, are clear evidence of the vitality of a culture which was perfectly adapted to its physical and economic environment, but which suddenly vanished at the time of the Spanish Conquest.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="585" unique="692" trans="0" lat="19.70444000" long="-101.19167000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Michoacan. Mairie de Morelia</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Morelia</site>
    <description>Built in the 16th century, Morelia is an outstanding example of urban planning which combines the ideas of the Spanish Renaissance with the Mesoamerican experience. Well-adapted to the slopes of the hill site, its streets still follow the original layout. More than 200 historic buildings, all in the region's characteristic pink stone, reflect the town's architectural history, revealing a masterly and eclectic blend of the medieval spirit with Renaissance, Baroque and neoclassical elements. Morelia was the birthplace of several important personalities of independent Mexico and has played a major role in the country's history.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="676" unique="800" trans="0" lat="22.76667000" long="-102.55556000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Zacatecas State, Zacatecas Municipality</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Zacatecas</site>
    <description>Founded in 1546 after the discovery of a rich silver lode, Zacatecas reached the height of its prosperity in the 16th and 17th centuries. Built on the steep slopes of a narrow valley, the town has breathtaking views and there are many old buildings, both religious and civil. The cathedral, built between 1730 and 1760, dominates the centre of the town. It is notable for its harmonious design and the Baroque profusion of its façades, where European and indigenous decorative elements are found side by side.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="702" unique="830" trans="0" lat="18.93472000" long="-98.89778000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Morelos and Puebla States Municipalities: Atlatlauhcan, Cuernavaca, Tetela del Volcan, Yautepec, Ocuituco, Tepoztlan, Tlayacapan, Totolapan, Yecapixtla and Zacualpan de Amilpas in Morelos. Calpan, Huetotzingo and Tochimilco in Puebla.</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Earliest 16th-Century Monasteries on the Slopes of Popocatepetl</site>
    <description>These 14 monasteries stand on the slopes of Popocatepetl, to the south-east of Mexico City. They are in an excellent state of conservation and are good examples of the architectural style adopted by the first missionaries – Franciscans, Dominicans and Augustinians – who converted the indigenous populations to Christianity in the early 16th century. They also represent an example of a new architectural concept in which open spaces are of renewed importance. The influence of this style is felt throughout the Mexican territory and even beyond its borders.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="714" unique="845" trans="0" lat="27.65556000" long="-112.91611000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State: Lower California Sud Municipality</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Rock Paintings of the Sierra de San Francisco</site>
    <description>From c. 100 B.C. to A.D. 1300, the Sierra de San Francisco (in the El Vizcaino reserve, in Baja California) was home to a people who have now disappeared but who left one of the most outstanding collections of rock  paintings in the world. They are remarkably well-preserved because of the dry climate and the inaccessibility of the site. Showing human figures and many animal species and illustrating the relationship between humans and their environment, the paintings reveal a highly sophisticated culture. Their composition and size, as well as the precision of the outlines and the variety of colours, but especially the number of sites, make this an impressive testimony to a unique artistic tradition.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="791" unique="935" trans="0" lat="20.36166667" long="-89.77027778">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Etat de Yucatan, municipalites Muna et Santa Elena</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Pre-Hispanic Town of Uxmal</site>
    <description>The Mayan town of Uxmal, in Yucatán, was founded c. A.D. 700 and had some 25,000 inhabitants. The layout of the buildings, which date from between 700 and 1000, reveals a knowledge of astronomy. The Pyramid of the Soothsayer, as the Spaniards called it, dominates the ceremonial centre, which has well-designed buildings decorated with a profusion of symbolic motifs and sculptures depicting Chaac, the god of rain. The ceremonial sites of Uxmal, Kabah, Labna and Sayil are considered the high points of Mayan art and architecture.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="792" unique="936" trans="0" lat="20.58333333" long="-100.36666670">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Etat Querétaro, municipalité de Querétaro</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Monuments Zone of Querétaro</site>
    <description>The old colonial town of Querétaro is unusual in having retained the geometric street plan of the Spanish conquerors side by side with the twisting alleys of the Indian quarters. The Otomi, the Tarasco, the Chichimeca and the Spanish lived together peacefully in the town, which is notable for the many ornate civil and religious Baroque monuments from its golden age in the 17th and 18th centuries.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="862" unique="1013" trans="0" lat="18.60833333" long="-95.65833333">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Veracruz, Tlacotalpan Municipality</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Monuments Zone of Tlacotalpan</site>
    <description>Tlacotalpan, a Spanish colonial river port on the Gulf coast of Mexico, was founded in the mid-16th century. It has preserved its original urban fabric to a remarkable degree, with wide streets, colonnaded houses in a profusion of styles and colours, and many mature trees in the public open spaces and private gardens.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="895" unique="1046" trans="0" lat="19.84639000" long="-90.53722000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Campeche</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Historic Fortified Town of Campeche</site>
    <description>Campeche is a typical example of a harbour town from the Spanish colonial period in the New World. The historic centre has kept its outer walls and system of fortifications, designed to defend this Caribbean port against attacks from the sea.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="939" unique="1094" trans="0" lat="18.81028000" long="-99.27500000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Municipalities of Temixco and  Miacatlan, Morelos State</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Archaeological Monuments Zone of Xochicalco</site>
    <description>Xochicalco is an exceptionally well-preserved example of a fortified political, religious and commercial centre from the troubled period of 650–900 that followed the break-up of the great Mesoamerican states such as Teotihuacan, Monte Albán, Palenque and Tikal.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1061" unique="1238" trans="0" lat="18.12250000" long="-89.78333000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2002</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Calakmul Municipality, Campeche Province</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Ancient Maya City of Calakmul, Campeche</site>
    <description>Calakmul, an important Maya site set deep in the tropical forest of the Tierras Bajas of southern Mexico, played a key role in the history of this region for more than twelve centuries. Its imposing structures and its characteristic overall layout are remarkably well preserved and give a vivid picture of life in an ancient Maya capital.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1079" unique="1256" trans="0" lat="21.20438889" long="-99.46411111">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Querétaro de Arteaga (Sierra Gorda region)</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Franciscan Missions in the Sierra Gorda of Querétaro</site>
    <description>The five Franciscan missions of Sierra Gorda were built during the last phase of the conversion to Christianity of the interior of Mexico in the mid-18th century and became an important reference for the continuation of the evangelization of California, Arizona and Texas. The richly decorated church façades are of special interest as they represent an example of the joint creative efforts of the missionaries and the Indios. The rural settlements that grew around the missions have retained their vernacular character.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1136" unique="1316" trans="0" lat="19.41833333" long="-99.19833333">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Mexico City</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Luis Barragán House and Studio</site>
    <description>Built in 1948, the House and Studio of architect Luis Barragán in the suburbs of Mexico City represents an outstanding example of the architect’s creative work in the post-Second World War period. The concrete building, totalling 1,161 m2, consists of a ground floor and two upper storeys, as well as a small private garden. Barragán’s work integrated modern and traditional artistic and vernacular currents and elements into a new synthesis, which has been greatly influential, especially in the contemporary design of gardens, plazas and landscapes.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1250" unique="1427" trans="0" lat="19.33222222" long="-99.18805556">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Mexico City</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Central University City Campus of the &lt;i&gt;Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México&lt;/i&gt; (UNAM)</site>
    <description>The ensemble of buildings, sports facilities and open spaces of the Central University City Campus of the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM), was built from 1949 to 1952 by more than 60 architects, engineers and artists who were involved in the project. As a result, the campus constitutes a unique example of 20th-century modernism integrating urbanism, architecture, engineering, landscape design and fine arts with references to local traditions, especially to Mexico&amp;#39;s pre-Hispanic past. The ensemble embodies social and cultural values of universal significance. Universally recognized, the campus is one of the most significant icons of modernity in Latin America. It is also one of a very small number of projects anywhere in the world where the principles proposed by the modern movements in architecture and town planning, the ultimate purpose of which was to improve people&amp;#39;s quality of life, were thoroughly applied.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1182" unique="1559" trans="0" lat="27.62667000" long="-112.54583000">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>mx</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>States of Baja California, Baja California Sur, Sinora, Sinaloa, and Nayarit</location>
    <state>Mexico</state>
    <site>Islands and Protected Areas of the Gulf of California</site>
    <description>The site comprises 244 islands, islets and coastal areas that are located in the Gulf of California in north-eastern Mexico. The Sea of Cortez and its islands have been called a natural laboratory for the investigation of speciation. Moreover, almost all major oceanographic processes occurring in the planet’s oceans are present in the property, giving it extraordinary importance for study. The site is one of striking natural beauty in a dramatic setting formed by rugged islands with high cliffs and sandy beaches, which contrast with the brilliant reflection from the desert and the surrounding turquoise waters. It is home to 695 vascular plant species, more than in any marine and insular property on the World Heritage List. Equally exceptional is the number of fish species: 891, 90 of them endemic. The site, moreover, contains 39% of the world’s total number of species of marine mammals and a third of the world’s marine cetacean species.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="613" unique="728" trans="0" lat="12.39722000" long="-86.61028000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>ni</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Puerto Momotombo, Municipality of La Paz Centro, Department of León</location>
    <state>Nicaragua</state>
    <site>Ruins of León Viejo</site>
    <description>León Viejo is one of the oldest Spanish colonial settlements in the Americas. It did not develop and so its ruins are outstanding testimony to the social and economic structures of the Spanish Empire in the 16th century. Moreover, the site has immense archaeological potential.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="402" unique="465" trans="0" lat="-12.25000000" long="-71.75000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>pe</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Dep. Madre de Dios y Cusco.  Provincias: Manu y Paucartambo</location>
    <state>Peru</state>
    <site>Manú National Park</site>
    <description>This huge 1.5 million-ha park has successive tiers of vegetation rising from 150 to 4,200 m above sea-level. The tropical forest in the lower tiers is home to an unrivalled variety of animal and plant species. Some 850 species of birds have been identified and rare species such as the giant otter and the giant armadillo also find refuge there. Jaguars are often sighted in the park.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="64" unique="68" trans="0" lat="17.21666667" long="-89.61666667">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(iv)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>gt</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of El Peten</location>
    <state>Guatemala</state>
    <site>Tikal National Park</site>
    <description>In the heart of the jungle, surrounded by lush vegetation, lies one of the major sites of Mayan civilization, inhabited from the 6th century B.C. to the 10th century A.D. The ceremonial centre contains superb temples and palaces, and public squares accessed by means of ramps. Remains of dwellings are scattered throughout the surrounding countryside.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="65" unique="69" trans="0" lat="14.56666667" long="-90.66666667">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>gt</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of Sacatepéquez, Panchoy Valley</location>
    <state>Guatemala</state>
    <site>Antigua Guatemala</site>
    <description>Antigua, the capital of the Captaincy-General of Guatemala, was founded in the early 16th century. Built 1,500 m above sea-level, in an earthquake-prone region, it was largely destroyed by an earthquake in 1773 but its principal monuments are still preserved as ruins. In the space of under three centuries the city, which was built on a grid pattern inspired by the Italian Renaissance, acquired a number of superb monuments.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="129" unique="141" trans="0" lat="14.85000000" long="-89.13333000">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1980</inscribeDate>
    <code>hn</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Copán; westernmost part of the country</location>
    <state>Honduras</state>
    <site>Maya Site of Copan</site>
    <description>Discovered in 1570 by Diego García de Palacio, the ruins of Copán, one of the most important sites of the Mayan civilization, were not excavated until the 19th century. The ruined citadel and imposing public squares reveal the three main stages of development before the city was abandoned in the early 10th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="196" unique="217" trans="0" lat="15.74444444" long="-84.67500000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>hn</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Northeast of the country in the area known as the “Mosquitia Hondureña”</location>
    <state>Honduras</state>
    <site>Río Plátano Biosphere Reserve</site>
    <description>Located on the watershed of the Río Plátano, the reserve is one of the few remains of a tropical rainforest in Central America and has an abundant and varied plant and wildlife. In its mountainous landscape sloping down to the Caribbean coast, over 2,000 indigenous people have preserved their traditional way of life.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="2" unique="5" trans="0" lat="-0.00388889" long="-78.50000000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1978</inscribeDate>
    <code>ec</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Pinchinada, City and Canton of Quito</location>
    <state>Ecuador</state>
    <site>City of Quito</site>
    <description>Quito, the capital of Ecuador, was founded in the 16th century on the ruins of an Inca city and stands at an altitude of 2,850 m. Despite the 1917 earthquake, the city has the best-preserved, least altered historic centre in Latin America. The monasteries of San Francisco and Santo Domingo, and the Church and Jesuit College of La Compañía, with their rich interiors, are pure examples of the 'Baroque school of Quito', which is a fusion of Spanish, Italian, Moorish, Flemish and indigenous art.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="260" unique="290" trans="0" lat="-1.83333000" long="-78.33333000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>ec</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Provinces of Morona Santiago, Chimborazo and Tungurahua</location>
    <state>Ecuador</state>
    <site>Sangay National Park</site>
    <description>With its outstanding natural beauty and two active volcanoes, the park illustrates the entire spectrum of ecosystems, ranging from tropical rainforests to glaciers, with striking contrasts between the snowcapped peaks and the forests of the plains. Its isolation has encouraged the survival of indigenous species such as the mountain tapir and the Andean condor.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="863" unique="1014" trans="0" lat="-2.88333333" long="-78.98333333">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>ec</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Azuay</location>
    <state>Ecuador</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Santa Ana de los Ríos de Cuenca</site>
    <description>Santa Ana de los Ríos de Cuenca is set in a valley surrounded by the Andean mountains in the south of Ecuador. This inland colonial town (&lt;I&gt;entroterra&lt;/I&gt;), now the country's third city, was founded in 1557 on the rigorous planning guidelines issued 30 years earlier by the Spanish king Charles V. Cuenca still observes the formal orthogonal town plan that it has respected for 400 years. One of the region's agricultural and administrative centres, it has been a melting pot for local and immigrant populations. Cuenca's architecture, much of which dates from the 18th century, was 'modernized' in the economic prosperity of the 19th century as the city became a major exporter of quinine, straw hats and other products.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="675" unique="799" trans="0" lat="13.82750000" long="-89.36916667">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>sv</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of La Libertad, Canton Joya de Ceren, jurisdiction of San Juan Opico</location>
    <state>El Salvador</state>
    <site>Joya de Cerén Archaeological Site</site>
    <description>Joya de Cerén was a pre-Hispanic farming community that, like Pompeii and Herculaneum in Italy, was buried under an eruption of the Laguna Caldera volcano c. AD 600. Because of the exceptional condition of the remains, they provide an insight into the daily lives of the Central American populations who worked the land at that time.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="764" unique="900" trans="0" lat="16.75000000" long="-87.05833333">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>bz</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Belize District (sites I, II, III), Stann Creek District ( IV,V,VI), Toledo District (VII)</location>
    <state>Belize</state>
    <site>Belize Barrier Reef Reserve System</site>
    <description>The coastal area of Belize is an outstanding natural system consisting of the largest barrier reef in the northern hemisphere, offshore atolls, several hundred sand cays, mangrove forests, coastal lagoons and estuaries. The system’s seven sites illustrate the evolutionary history of reef development and are a significant habitat for threatened species, including marine turtles, manatees and the American marine crocodile.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="420" unique="484" trans="0" lat="-19.58361000" long="-65.75306000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>bo</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Potosi, Province of Potosi</location>
    <state>Bolivia</state>
    <site>City of Potosí</site>
    <description>In the 16th century, this area was regarded as the world’s largest industrial complex. The extraction of silver ore relied on a series of hydraulic mills. The site consists of the industrial monuments of the Cerro Rico, where water is provided by an intricate system of aqueducts and artificial lakes; the colonial town with the Casa de la Moneda; the Church of San Lorenzo; several patrician houses; and the barrios mitayos, the areas where the workers lived.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="355" unique="408" trans="0" lat="-25.68333000" long="-54.43333000">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1986</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Paraná State</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Iguaçu National Park</site>
    <description>The park shares with Iguazú National Park in Argentina one of the world’s largest and most impressive waterfalls, extending over some 2,700 m. It is home to many rare and endangered species of flora and fauna, among them the giant otter and the giant anteater. The clouds of spray produced by the waterfall are conducive to the growth of lush vegetation.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="445" unique="516" trans="0" lat="-15.78333000" long="-47.90000000">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Federal District</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Brasilia</site>
    <description>Brasilia, a capital created &lt;em&gt;ex nihilo&lt;/em&gt; in the centre of the country in 1956, was a landmark in the history of town planning. Urban planner Lucio Costa and architect Oscar Niemeyer intended that every element – from the layout of the residential and administrative districts (often compared to the shape of a bird in flight) to the symmetry of the buildings themselves – should be in harmony with the city’s overall design. The official buildings, in particular, are innovative and imaginative.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="606" unique="719" trans="0" lat="-8.41666667" long="-42.33333333">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Sud-est de Etat du Piaui – Communes de Sao Raimundo Nonato, Sao Joao do Piaui et Canto do Butriti</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Serra da Capivara National Park</site>
    <description>Many of the numerous rock shelters in the Serra da Capivara National Park are decorated with cave paintings, some more than 25,000 years old. They are an outstanding testimony to one of the oldest human communities of South America.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="821" unique="970" trans="0" lat="-2.51416667" long="-44.30250000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Maranhão State, Brasil’s North-East Region</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of São Luís</site>
    <description>The late 17th-century core of this historic town, founded by the French and occupied by the Dutch before coming under Portuguese rule, has preserved the original rectangular street plan in its entirety. Thanks to a period of economic stagnation in the early 20th century, an exceptional number of fine historic buildings have survived, making this an outstanding example of an Iberian colonial town.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="890" unique="1042" trans="0" lat="-18.23333333" long="-43.60000000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Minas Gerais</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of the Town of Diamantina</site>
    <description>Diamantina, a colonial village set like a jewel in a necklace of inhospitable rocky mountains, recalls the exploits of diamond prospectors in the 18th century and testifies to the triumph of human cultural and artistic endeavour over the environment.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="892" unique="1044" trans="0" lat="-16.50000000" long="-39.25000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Atlantic Coast, states of Bahia and Espirito Santo, northeast Brazil</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Discovery Coast Atlantic Forest Reserves</site>
    <description>The Discovery Coast Atlantic Forest Reserves, in the states of Bahia and Espírito Santo, consist of eight separate protected areas containing 112,000 ha of Atlantic forest and associated shrub (&lt;em&gt;restingas&lt;/em&gt;). The rainforests of Brazil’s Atlantic coast are the world’s richest in terms of biodiversity. The site contains a distinct range of species with a high level of endemism and reveals a pattern of evolution that is not only of great scientific interest but is also of importance for conservation.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="893" unique="1045" trans="0" lat="-24.16667000" long="-48.00000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Atlantic coast, states of Parana and Sao Paolo</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Atlantic Forest South-East Reserves</site>
    <description>The Atlantic Forest South-East Reserves, in the states of Paraná and São Paulo, contain some of the best and most extensive examples of Atlantic forest in Brazil. The 25 protected areas that make up the site (some 470,000 ha in total) display the biological wealth and evolutionary history of the last remaining Atlantic forests. From mountains covered by dense forests, down to wetlands, coastal islands with isolated mountains and dunes, the area comprises a rich natural environment of great scenic beauty.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="715" unique="846" trans="0" lat="-27.15000000" long="-109.45000000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>cl</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Easter Island province of the Valparaíso Region</location>
    <state>Chile</state>
    <site>Rapa Nui National Park</site>
    <description>Rapa Nui, the indigenous name of Easter Island, bears witness to a unique cultural phenomenon. A society of Polynesian origin that settled there c. A.D. 300 established a powerful, imaginative and original tradition of monumental sculpture and architecture, free from any external influence. From the 10th to the 16th century this society built shrines and erected enormous stone figures known as &lt;I&gt;moai&lt;/I&gt;, which created an unrivalled cultural landscape that continues to fascinate people throughout the world.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="959" unique="1123" trans="0" lat="-33.04063889" long="-71.62800000">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>cl</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Fifth Region, Province Valparaíso</location>
    <state>Chile</state>
    <site>Historic Quarter of the Seaport City of Valparaíso</site>
    <description>The colonial city of Valparaíso presents an excellent example of late 19th-century urban and architectural development in Latin America. In its natural amphitheatre-like setting, the city is characterized by a vernacular urban fabric adapted to the hillsides that are dotted with a great variety of church spires. It contrasts with the geometrical layout utilized in the plain. The city has well preserved its interesting early industrial infrastructures, such as the numerous ‘elevators’ on the steep hillsides.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1178" unique="1355" trans="0" lat="-20.20582000" long="-69.79406000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>cl</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Iquique</location>
    <state>Chile</state>
    <site>Humberstone and Santa Laura Saltpeter Works</site>
    <description>Humberstone and Santa Laura works contain over 200 former saltpeter works where workers from Chile, Peru and Bolivia lived in company towns and forged a distinctive communal pampinos culture. That culture is manifest in their rich language, creativity, and solidarity, and, above all, in their pioneering struggle for social justice, which had a profound impact on social history. Situated in the remote Pampas, one of the driest deserts on Earth, thousands of pampinos lived and worked in this hostile environment for over 60 years, from 1880, to process the largest deposit of saltpeter in the world, producing the fertilizer sodium nitrate that was to transform agricultural lands in North and South America, and in Europe, and produce great wealth for Chile. Because of the vulnerability of the structures and the impact of a recent earthquake, the site was also placed on the List of World Heritage in Danger to help mobilize resources for its conservation.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1214" unique="1391" trans="0" lat="-34.08444444" long="-70.38277778">
    <criteria>(ii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2006</inscribeDate>
    <code>cl</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Libertador General Bernardo O'Higgins Region, Province of Cachapoal, Municipality of Machali</location>
    <state>Chile</state>
    <site>Sewell Mining Town</site>
    <description>Situated at 2,000 m in the Andes, 60 km to the east of Rancagua, in an environment marked by extremes of climate, Sewell Mining Town was built by the Braden Copper company in 1905 to house workers at what was to become the world’s largest underground copper mine, El Teniente. It is an outstanding example of the company towns that were born in many remote parts of the world from the fusion of local labour and resources from an industrialized nation, to mine and process high-value natural resources. The town was built on a terrain too steep for wheeled vehicles around a large central staircase rising from the railway station. Along its route formal squares of irregular shape with ornamental trees and plants constituted the main public spaces or squares of the town. The buildings lining the streets are timber, often painted in vivid green, yellow, red and blue. At its peak Sewell numbered 15,000 inhabitants, but was largely abandoned in the 1970s.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="940" unique="1096" trans="0" lat="5.82611000" long="-55.15000000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2002</inscribeDate>
    <code>sr</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>District of Paramaribo</location>
    <state>Suriname</state>
    <site>Historic Inner City of Paramaribo</site>
    <description>Paramaribo is a former Dutch colonial town from the 17th and 18th centuries planted on the northern coast of tropical South America. The original and highly characteristic street plan of the historic centre remains intact. Its buildings illustrate the gradual fusion of Dutch architectural influence with traditional local techniques and materials.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1017" unique="1187" trans="0" lat="4.00000000" long="-56.50000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>sr</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>District Sipaliwini</location>
    <state>Suriname</state>
    <site>Central Suriname Nature Reserve</site>
    <description>The Central Suriname Nature Reserve comprises 1.6 million ha of primary tropical forest of west-central Suriname. It protects the upper watershed of the Coppename River and the headwaters of the Lucie, Oost, Zuid, Saramaccz, and Gran Rio rivers and covers a range of topography and ecosystems of notable conservation value due to its pristine state. Its montane and lowland forests contain a high diversity of plant life with more than 5,000 vascular plant species collected to date. The Reserve&amp;#39;s animals are typical of the region and include the jaguar, giant armadillo, giant river otter, tapir, sloths, eight species of primates and 400 bird species such as harpy eagle, Guiana cock-of-the-rock, and scarlet macaw.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="747" unique="881" trans="0" lat="-34.46777778" long="-57.85333333">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>uy</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department de Colonia</location>
    <state>Uruguay</state>
    <site>Historic Quarter of the City of Colonia del Sacramento</site>
    <description>Founded by the Portuguese in 1680 on the Río de la Plata, the city was of strategic importance in resisting the Spanish. After being disputed for a century, it was finally lost by its founders. The well-preserved urban landscape illustrates the successful fusion of the Portuguese, Spanish and post-colonial styles.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="658" unique="779" trans="0" lat="11.40000000" long="-69.68333333">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>ve</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Falcon</location>
    <state>Venezuela (Bolivarian Republic of)</state>
    <site>Coro and its Port</site>
    <description>With its earthen constructions unique to the Caribbean, Coro is the only surviving example of a rich fusion of local traditions with Spanish Mudéjar and Dutch architectural techniques. One of the first colonial towns (founded in 1527), it has some 602 historic buildings.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="701" unique="829" trans="0" lat="5.33333000" long="-61.50000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>ve</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Bolivar State</location>
    <state>Venezuela (Bolivarian Republic of)</state>
    <site>Canaima National Park</site>
    <description>Canaima National Park is spread over 3 million ha in south-eastern Venezuela along the border between Guyana and Brazil. Roughly 65% of the park is covered by table mountain (tepui) formations. The tepuis constitute a unique biogeological entity and are of great geological interest. The sheer cliffs and waterfalls, including the world's highest (1,000 m), form a spectacular landscape.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="986" unique="1150" trans="0" lat="10.49073000" long="-66.89068000">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>ve</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Municipality of Libertador, Caracas</location>
    <state>Venezuela (Bolivarian Republic of)</state>
    <site>Ciudad Universitaria de Caracas</site>
    <description>The Ciudad Universitaria de Caracas, built to the design of the architect Carlos Raúl Villanueva, between 1940 and 1960, is an outstanding example of the Modern Movement in architecture. The university campus integrates the large number of buildings and functions into a clearly articulated ensemble, including masterpieces of modern architecture and visual arts, such as the Aula Magna with the 'Clouds' of Alexander Calder, the Olympic Stadium, and the Covered Plaza.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="145" unique="160" trans="0" lat="-50.00000000" long="-73.24944000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Santa Cruz</location>
    <state>Argentina</state>
    <site>Los Glaciares</site>
    <description>The Los Glaciares National Park is an area of exceptional natural beauty, with rugged, towering mountains and numerous glacial lakes, including Lake Argentino, which is 160 km long. At its farthest end, three glaciers meet to dump their effluvia into the milky grey glacial water, launching massive igloo icebergs into the lake with thunderous splashes.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="303" unique="340" trans="0" lat="-25.51805556" long="-54.13333333">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province: Misiones - Region: Nord-Est</location>
    <state>Argentina</state>
    <site>Iguazu National Park</site>
    <description>The semicircular waterfall at the heart of this site is some 80 m high and 2,700 m in diameter and is situated on a basaltic line spanning the border between Argentina and Brazil. Made up of many cascades producing vast sprays of water, it is one of the most spectacular waterfalls in the world. The surrounding subtropical rainforest has over 2,000 species of vascular plants and is home to the typical wildlife of the region: tapirs, giant anteaters, howler monkeys, ocelots, jaguars and caymans.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="936" unique="1091" trans="0" lat="-47.15000000" long="-70.66666667">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Patagonia Region, Santa Cruz Province</location>
    <state>Argentina</state>
    <site>Cueva de las Manos, Río Pinturas</site>
    <description>The Cueva de las Manos, Río Pinturas, contains an exceptional assemblage of cave art, executed between 13,000 and 9,500 years ago. It takes its name (Cave of the Hands) from the stencilled outlines of human hands in the cave, but there are also many depictions of animals, such as guanacos (&lt;I&gt;Lama guanicoe&lt;/I&gt;), still commonly found in the region, as well as hunting scenes. The people responsible for the paintings may have been the ancestors of the historic hunter-gatherer communities of Patagonia found by European settlers in the 19th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="937" unique="1092" trans="0" lat="-42.50000000" long="-64.00000000">
    <criteria>(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Chubut. Patagonia</location>
    <state>Argentina</state>
    <site>Península Valdés</site>
    <description>Península Valdés in Patagonia is a site of global significance for the conservation of marine mammals. It is home to an important breeding population of the endangered southern right whale as well as important breeding populations of southern elephant seals and southern sea lions. The orcas in this area have developed a unique hunting strategy to adapt to local coastal conditions.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="966" unique="1130" trans="0" lat="-30.00000000" long="-68.00000000">
    <criteria>(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Provinces of San Juan and La Rioja</location>
    <state>Argentina</state>
    <site>Ischigualasto / Talampaya Natural Parks</site>
    <description>These two contiguous parks, extending over 275,300 ha in the desert region on the western border of the Sierra Pampeanas of central Argentina, contain the most complete continental fossil record known from the Triassic Period (245-208 million years ago). Six geological formations in the parks contain fossils of a wide range of ancestors of mammals, dinosaurs and plants revealing the evolution of vertebrates and the nature of palaeo-environments in the Triassic Period.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="995" unique="1159" trans="0" lat="-31.42056000" long="-64.19111000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Cordoba</location>
    <state>Argentina</state>
    <site>Jesuit Block and Estancias of Córdoba</site>
    <description>The Jesuit Block in Córdoba, heart of the former Jesuit Province of Paraguay, contains the core buildings of the Jesuit system: the university, the church and residence of the Society of Jesus, and the college. Along with the five estancias, or farming estates, they contain religious and secular buildings, which illustrate the unique religious, social, and economic experiment carried out in the world for a period of over 150 years in the 17th and 18th centuries.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="529" unique="619" trans="0" lat="-16.00000000" long="-60.50000000">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1990</inscribeDate>
    <code>bo</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of Santa Cruz</location>
    <state>Bolivia</state>
    <site>Jesuit Missions of the Chiquitos</site>
    <description>Between 1696 and 1760, six ensembles of reducciones (settlements of Christianized Indians) inspired by the ‘ideal cities’ of the 16th-century philosophers were founded by the Jesuits in a style that married Catholic architecture with local traditions. The six that remain – San Francisco Javier, Concepción, Santa Ana, San Miguel, San Rafael and San José – make up a living heritage on the former territory of the Chiquitos.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="566" unique="668" trans="0" lat="-19.04306000" long="-65.25917000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>bo</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department de Chuquisaca, Province Oropeza</location>
    <state>Bolivia</state>
    <site>Historic City of Sucre</site>
    <description>Sucre, the first capital of Bolivia, was founded by the Spanish in the first half of the 16th century. Its many well-preserved 16th-century religious buildings, such as San Lázaro, San Francisco and Santo Domingo, illustrate the blending of local architectural traditions with styles imported from Europe.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="567" unique="670" trans="0" lat="-16.55833333" long="-68.67778000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>bo</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Ingavi, Department of La Paz</location>
    <state>Bolivia</state>
    <site>Tiwanaku: Spiritual and Political Centre of the Tiwanaku Culture</site>
    <description>The city of Tiwanaku, capital of a powerful pre-Hispanic empire that dominated a large area of the southern Andes and beyond, reached its apogee between 500 and 900 AD. Its monumental remains testify to the cultural and political significance of this civilisation, which is distinct from any of the other pre-Hispanic empires of the Americas.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="883" unique="1035" trans="0" lat="-18.16666667" long="-63.81666667">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>bo</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Florida, Department of Santa Cruz</location>
    <state>Bolivia</state>
    <site>Fuerte de Samaipata</site>
    <description>The archaeological site of Samaipata consists of two parts: the hill with its many carvings, believed to have been the ceremonial centre of the old town (14th–16th centuries), and the area to the south of the hill, which formed the administrative and residential district. The huge sculptured rock, dominating the town below, is a unique testimony to pre-Hispanic traditions and beliefs, and has no parallel anywhere in the Americas.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="967" unique="1131" trans="0" lat="-14.26667000" long="-60.86667000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>bo</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Velasco Province, Santa Cruz Department</location>
    <state>Bolivia</state>
    <site>Noel Kempff Mercado National Park</site>
    <description>The National Park is one of the largest (1,523,000 ha) and most intact parks in the Amazon Basin. With an altitudinal range of 200 m to nearly 1,000 m, it is the site of a rich mosaic of habitat types from Cerrado savannah and forest to upland evergreen Amazonian forests. The park boasts an evolutionary history dating back over a billion years to the Precambrian period. An estimated 4,000 species of flora as well as over 600 bird species and viable populations of many globally endangered or threatened vertebrate species live in the park.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="993" unique="1157" trans="0" lat="-15.93328000" long="-50.13336000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2001</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Goiás</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of the Town of Goiás</site>
    <description>Goiás testifies to the occupation and colonization of the lands of central Brazil in the 18th and 19th centuries. The urban layout is an example of the organic development of a mining town, adapted to the conditions of the site. Although modest, both public and private architecture form a harmonious whole, thanks to the coherent use of local materials and vernacular techniques.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="998" unique="1163" trans="0" lat="-2.33333333" long="-62.00833333">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Amazonas</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Central Amazon Conservation Complex</site>
    <description>The Central Amazon Conservation Complex makes up the largest protected area in the Amazon Basin (over 6 million hectares) and is one of the planet’s richest regions in terms of biodiversity. It also includes an important sample of varzea ecosystems, igapó forests, lakes and channels which take the form of a constantly evolving aquatic mosaic that is home to the largest array of electric fish in the world. The site protects key threatened species, including giant arapaima fish, the Amazonian manatee, the black caiman and two species of river dolphin.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="999" unique="1164" trans="0" lat="-17.71667000" long="-57.38333000">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Southwest of the State of Mato Grosso and Northwest of the State of Mato Grosso do Sul, adjacent to the Brazil/Bolivian borders</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Pantanal Conservation Area</site>
    <description>The Pantanal Conservation Complex consists of a cluster of four protected areas with a total area of 187,818 ha. Located in western central Brazil at the south-west corner of the State of Mato Grosso, the site represents 1.3% of Brazil's Pantanal region, one of the world's largest freshwater wetland ecosystems. The headwaters of the region's two major river systems, the Cuiabá and the Paraguay rivers, are located here, and the abundance and diversity of its vegetation and animal life are spectacular.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1000" unique="1166" trans="0" lat="-3.85794444" long="-32.42511111">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2001</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Pernambuco and Rio Grande do Norte States</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Brazilian Atlantic Islands: Fernando de Noronha and Atol das Rocas Reserves</site>
    <description>Peaks of the Southern Atlantic submarine ridge form the Fernando de Noronha Archipelago and Rocas Atoll off the coast of Brazil. They represent a large proportion of the island surface of the South Atlantic and their rich waters are extremely important for the breeding and feeding of tuna, shark, turtle and marine mammals. The islands are home to the largest concentration of tropical seabirds in the Western Atlantic. Baia de Golfinhos has an exceptional population of resident dolphin and at low tide the Rocas Atoll provides a spectacular seascape of lagoons and tidal pools teeming with fish.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1035" unique="1208" trans="0" lat="-14.00569444" long="-47.68461111">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2001</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Central Brazil Plateau, State of Goiás</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Cerrado Protected Areas: Chapada dos Veadeiros and Emas National Parks</site>
    <description>The two sites included in the designation contain flora and fauna and key habitats that characterize the Cerrado – one of the world’s oldest and most diverse tropical ecosystems. For millennia, these sites have served as refuge for several species during periods of climate change and will be vital for maintaining the biodiversity of the Cerrado region during future climate fluctuations.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="275" unique="326" trans="1" lat="-28.54333333" long="-54.26583333">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar,br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil; Province of Misiones, Argentina</location>
    <state>Argentina,Brazil</state>
    <site>Jesuit Missions of the Guaranis: San Ignacio Mini, Santa Ana, Nuestra Señora de Loreto and Santa Maria Mayor (Argentina), Ruins of Sao Miguel das Missoes (Brazil)</site>
    <description>The ruins of São Miguel das Missões in Brazil, and those of San Ignacio Miní, Santa Ana, Nuestra Señora de Loreto and Santa María la Mayor in Argentina, lie at the heart of a tropical forest. They are the impressive remains of five Jesuit missions, built in the land of the Guaranis during the 17th and 18th centuries. Each is characterized by a specific layout and a different state of conservation.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="285" unique="319" trans="0" lat="10.41666667" long="-75.53333333">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>co</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Bolivar Department</location>
    <state>Colombia</state>
    <site>Port, Fortresses and Group of Monuments, Cartagena</site>
    <description>Situated in a bay in the Caribbean Sea, Cartagena has the most extensive fortifications in South America. A system of zones divides the city into three neighbourhoods: San Pedro, with the cathedral and many Andalusian-style palaces; San Diego, where merchants and the middle class lived; and Gethsemani, the 'popular quarter'.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="711" unique="841" trans="0" lat="7.66666667" long="-77.00000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>co</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Provinces of Antioquia and Choco’</location>
    <state>Colombia</state>
    <site>Los Katíos National Park</site>
    <description>Extending over 72,000 ha in north-western Colombia, Los Katios National Park comprises low hills, forests and humid plains. An exceptional biological diversity is found in the park, which is home to many threatened animal species, as well as many endemic plants.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="742" unique="876" trans="0" lat="9.23333333" long="-74.43333333">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>co</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Bolívar Department</location>
    <state>Colombia</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Santa Cruz de Mompox</site>
    <description>Founded in 1540 on the banks of the River Magdalena, Mompox played a key role in the Spanish colonization of northern South America. From the 16th to the 19th century the city developed parallel to the river, with the main street acting as a dyke. The historic centre has preserved the harmony and unity of the urban landscape. Most of the buildings are still used for their original purposes, providing an exceptional picture of what a Spanish colonial city was like.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="743" unique="877" trans="0" lat="2.58333333" long="-76.03333333">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>co</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of Cauca, in the jurisdiction of the municipality of Inza, in the “corregimiento” of San Andres de Pisimbalá</location>
    <state>Colombia</state>
    <site>National Archeological Park of Tierradentro</site>
    <description>Several monumental statues of human figures can be seen in the park, which also contains many hypogea dating from the 6th to the 10th century. These huge underground tombs (some burial chambers are up to 12 m wide) are decorated with motifs that reproduce the internal decor of homes of the period. They reveal the social complexity and cultural wealth of a pre-Hispanic society in the northern Andes.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="744" unique="878" trans="0" lat="1.91666667" long="-76.23333333">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>co</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Department of Huila: Municipalities of San Augustin and San José de Isnos</location>
    <state>Colombia</state>
    <site>San Agustín Archeological Park</site>
    <description>The largest group of religious monuments and megalithic sculptures in South America stands in a wild, spectacular landscape. Gods and mythical animals are skilfully represented in styles ranging from abstract to realist. These works of art display the creativity and imagination of a northern Andean culture that flourished from the 1st to the 8th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="124" unique="136" trans="0" lat="-20.38888889" long="-43.50555556">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1980</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Minas Gerais</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Historic Town of Ouro Preto</site>
    <description>Founded at the end of the 17th century, Ouro Preto (Black Gold) was the focal point of the gold rush and Brazil’s golden age in the 18th century. With the exhaustion of the gold mines in the 19th century, the city’s influence declined but many churches, bridges and fountains remain as a testimony to its past prosperity and the exceptional talent of the Baroque sculptor Aleijadinho.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="189" unique="210" trans="0" lat="-8.01333333" long="-34.84500000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>State of Pernambuco, North-East Region of Brazil</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of the Town of Olinda</site>
    <description>Founded in the 16th century by the Portuguese, the town’s history is linked to the sugar-cane industry. Rebuilt after being looted by the Dutch, its basic urban fabric dates from the 18th century. The harmonious balance between the buildings, gardens, 20 Baroque churches, convents and numerous small passos (chapels) all contribute to Olinda’s particular charm.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="309" unique="348" trans="0" lat="-12.96666667" long="-38.50000000">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>br</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Bahia State, north-east region of Brazil</location>
    <state>Brazil</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Salvador de Bahia</site>
    <description>As the first capital of Brazil, from 1549 to 1763, Salvador de Bahia witnessed the blending of European, African and Amerindian cultures. It was also, from 1558, the first slave market in the New World, with slaves arriving to work on the sugar plantations. The city has managed to preserve many outstanding Renaissance buildings. A special feature of the old town are the brightly coloured houses, often decorated with fine stucco-work.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="205" unique="226" trans="1" lat="9.40708333" long="-82.93880556">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>cr</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Provincias de Bocas del Toro y Chiriqui, Panama; San Jose, Cartago, Limon and Puntarenas Provinces, Costa Rica</location>
    <state>Costa Rica</state>
    <site>Talamanca Range-La Amistad Reserves / La Amistad National Park</site>
    <description>The location of this unique site in Central America, where Quaternary glaciers have left their mark, has allowed the fauna and flora of North and South America to interbreed. Tropical rainforests cover most of the area. Four different Indian tribes inhabit this property, which benefits from close co-operation between Costa Rica and Panama.</description>
  </row>
   <row id="205" unique="226" trans="1" lat="9.40708333" long="-82.93880556">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>pa</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Provincias de Bocas del Toro y Chiriqui, Panama; San Jose, Cartago, Limon and Puntarenas Provinces, Costa Rica</location>
    <state>Panama</state>
    <site>Talamanca Range-La Amistad Reserves / La Amistad National Park</site>
    <description>The location of this unique site in Central America, where Quaternary glaciers have left their mark, has allowed the fauna and flora of North and South America to interbreed. Tropical rainforests cover most of the area. Four different Indian tribes inhabit this property, which benefits from close co-operation between Costa Rica and Panama.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="820" unique="969" trans="0" lat="5.53333333" long="-87.06666667">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>cr</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Puntarenas, South Eastern Tropical Pacific</location>
    <state>Costa Rica</state>
    <site>Cocos Island National Park</site>
    <description>Cocos Island National Park, located 550 km off the Pacific coast of Costa Rica, is the only island in the tropical eastern Pacific with a tropical rainforest. Its position as the first point of contact with the northern equatorial counter-current, and the myriad interactions between the island and the surrounding marine ecosystem, make the area an ideal laboratory for the study of biological processes. The underwater world of the national park has become famous due to the attraction it holds for divers, who rate it as one of the best places in the world to view large pelagic species such as sharks, rays, tuna and dolphins.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="928" unique="1083" trans="0" lat="10.85000000" long="-85.61666667">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>cr</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Guanacaste and Alajuela provinces</location>
    <state>Costa Rica</state>
    <site>Area de Conservación Guanacaste</site>
    <description>The Area de Conservación Guanacaste (inscribed in 1999), was extended with the addition of a 15,000 ha private property, St Elena. It contains important natural habitats for the conservation of biological diversity, including the best dry forest habitats from Central America to northern Mexico and key habitats for endangered or rare plant and animal species. The site demonstrates significant ecological processes in both its terrestrial and marine-coastal environments.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1116" unique="1295" trans="0" lat="-23.19986111" long="-65.34886111">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>ar</code>
    <region>Latin America</region>
    <location>Province of Juyuy</location>
    <state>Argentina</state>
    <site>Quebrada de Humahuaca</site>
    <description>Quebrada de Humahuaca follows the line of a major cultural route, the Camino Inca, along the spectacular valley of the Rio Grande, from its source in the cold high desert plateau of the High Andean lands to its confluence with the Rio Leone some 150 km to the south. The valley shows substantial evidence of its use as a major trade route over the past 10,000 years. It features visible traces of prehistoric hunter-gatherer communities, of the Inca Empire (15th to 16th centuries) and of the fight for independence in the16th and 20th centuries.</description>
  </row>
</worldheritage>