<worldheritage promo="UNESCO">
    <row id="439" unique="510" trans="0" lat="41.79416667" long="123.44694440">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location />
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Imperial Palaces of the Ming and Qing Dynasties in Beijing and Shenyang</site>
    <description>Seat of supreme power for over five centuries (1416-1911), the Forbidden City in Beijing, with its landscaped gardens and many buildings (whose nearly 10,000 rooms contain furniture and works of art), constitutes a priceless testimony to Chinese civilization during the Ming and Qing dynasties. The Imperial Palace of the Qing Dynasty in Shenyang consists of 114 buildings constructed between 1625–26 and 1783. It contains an important library and testifies to the foundation of the last dynasty that ruled China, before it expanded its power to the centre of the country and moved the capital to Beijing. This palace then became auxiliary to the Imperial Palace in Beijing. This remarkable architectural edifice offers important historical testimony to the history of the Qing Dynasty and to the cultural traditions of the Manchu and other tribes in the north of China.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="640" unique="760" trans="0" lat="29.33333000" long="110.50000000">
    <criteria>(vii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>The Wulingyuan District of the City of Dayong, Hunan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Wulingyuan Scenic and Historic Interest Area</site>
    <description>A spectacular area stretching over more than 26,000 ha in China's Hunan Province, the site is dominated by more than 3,000 narrow sandstone pillars and peaks, many over 200 m high. Between the peaks lie ravines and gorges with streams, pools and waterfalls, some 40 caves, and two large natural bridges. In addition to the striking beauty of the landscape, the region is also noted for the fact that it is home to a number of endangered plant and animal species.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="881" unique="1033" trans="0" lat="39.84555556" long="116.44472220">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Tiantan Park, Beijing</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Temple of Heaven: an Imperial Sacrificial Altar in Beijing</site>
    <description>The Temple of Heaven, founded in the first half of the 15th century, is a dignified complex of fine cult buildings set in gardens and surrounded by historic pine woods. In its overall layout and that of its individual buildings, it symbolizes the relationship between earth and heaven – the human world and God's world – which stands at the heart of Chinese cosmogony, and also the special role played by the emperors within that relationship.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="707" unique="837" trans="0" lat="29.65792000" long="91.11717000">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Lhasa, Tibet Autonomous Region</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Historic Ensemble of the Potala Palace, Lhasa</site>
    <description>The Potala Palace, winter palace of the Dalai Lama since the 7th century, symbolizes Tibetan Buddhism and its central role in the traditional administration of Tibet. The complex, comprising the White and Red Palaces with their ancillary buildings, is built on Red Mountain in the centre of Lhasa Valley, at an altitude of 3,700m. Also founded in the 7th century, the Jokhang Temple Monastery is an exceptional Buddhist religious complex. Norbulingka, the Dalai Lama&amp;#39;s former summer palace, constructed in the 18th century, is a masterpiece of Tibetan art. The beauty and originality of the architecture of these three sites, their rich ornamentation and harmonious integration in a striking landscape, add to their historic and religious interest.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1004" unique="1172" trans="0" lat="41.70722222" long="124.79388890">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Nanjing City, Jiangsu Province (Xiaoling Tomb); Changping District, Beijing (Ming Tombs)</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Imperial Tombs of the Ming and Qing Dynasties</site>
    <description>It represents the addition of three Imperial Tombs of the Qing Dynasty in Liaoning to the Ming tombs inscribed in 2000 and 2003. The Three Imperial Tombs of the Qing Dynasty in Liaoning Province include the Yongling Tomb, the Fuling Tomb, and the Zhaoling Tomb, all built in the 17th century. Constructed for the founding emperors of the Qing Dynasty and their ancestors, the tombs follow the precepts of traditional Chinese geomancy and fengshui theory. They feature rich decoration of stone statues and carvings and tiles with dragon motifs, illustrating the development of the funerary architecture of the Qing Dynasty. The three tomb complexes, and their numerous edifices, combine traditions inherited from previous dynasties and new features of Manchu civilization.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1114" unique="1293" trans="0" lat="36.12666667" long="114.31388889">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2006</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Henan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Yin Xu</site>
    <description>The archaeological site of Yin Xu, close to Anyang City, some 500 km south of Beijing, is an ancient capital city of the late Shang Dynasty (1300 - 1046 BC). It testifies to the golden age of early Chinese culture, crafts and sciences, a time of great prosperity of the Chinese Bronze Age. A number of royal tombs and palaces, prototypes of later Chinese architecture, have been unearthed on the site, including the Palace and Royal Ancestral Shrines Area, with more than 80 house foundations, and the only tomb of a member of the royal family of the Shang Dynasty to have remained intact, the Tomb of Fu Hao. The large number and superb craftsmanship of the burial accessories found there bear testimony to the advanced level of Shang crafts industry. Inscriptions on oracle bones found in Yin Xu bear invaluable testimony to the development of one of the world’s oldest writing systems, ancient beliefs and social systems.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1112" unique="1459" trans="0" lat="22.28551944" long="112.56586111">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Guangdong Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Kaiping Diaolou and Villages</site>
    <description>Kaiping Diaolou and Villages, feature the Diaolou, multi-storied defensive village houses in Kaiping, Guangdong Province, which display a complex and flamboyant fusion of Chinese and Western structural and decorative forms. They reflect the significant role of émigré Kaiping people in the development of several countries in South Asia, Australasia, and North America, during the late 19th and early 20th centuries, and the close links between overseas Kaiping and their ancestral homes. The property inscribed here consists of four groups totalling 20 Diaolou, representing some 1,800 tower houses in their village settings. They reflect the culmination of almost five centuries of tower-house building and the still strong links between Kaiping and the Chinese Diaspora. These buildings take three forms: communal towers built by several families and used as temporary refuge, of which 473 remain; residential towers built by individual rich families and used as fortified residences, of which 1,149 survive; and watch towers, the latest development, which account for 221 of the buildings. Built of stone, pise (compressed earth), brick or concrete, these buildings represent a complex and confident fusion between Chinese and western architectural styles. Retaining a harmonious relationship with the surrounding agricultural landscape, the Diaolou testify to the final flowering of local building traditions that started in the Ming period in response to local banditry.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1091" unique="1269" trans="0" lat="38.86305556" long="125.41500000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>kp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Pyongyang, South Phyongan Province, Nampho, South Hwangghae Province</location>
    <state>Democratic People's Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Complex of Koguryo Tombs</site>
    <description>The property includes several group and individual tombs - totalling about 30 individual tombs - from the later period of the Koguryo Kingdom, one of the strongest kingdoms in nowadays northeast China and half of the Korean peninsula between the 3rd century BC to 7th century AD. The tombs, many with beautiful wall paintings, are almost the only remains of this culture. Only about 90 out of more than 10,000 Koguryo tombs discovered in China and Korea so far, have wall paintings. Almost half of these tombs are located on this site and they are thought to have been made for the burial of kings, members of the royal family and the aristocracy. These paintings offer a unique testimony to daily life of this period.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="255" unique="285" trans="0" lat="27.09444000" long="77.66417000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1986</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Uttar Pradesh, Agra District</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Fatehpur Sikri</site>
    <description>Built during the second half of the 16th century by the Emperor Akbar, Fatehpur Sikri (the City of Victory) was the capital of the Mughal Empire for only some 10 years. The complex of monuments and temples, all in a uniform architectural style, includes one of the largest mosques in India, the Jama Masjid.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="944" unique="1102" trans="0" lat="11.51028000" long="76.93583000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>States of West Bengal and Tamil Nadu</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Mountain Railways of India</site>
    <description>The site includes the Darjeeling Himalayan Railway, inscribed in 1999. The site now encompasses the Nilgiri Mountain Railway, a 46 km long metre-gauge single-track railway in Tamil Nadu State. Its construction was first proposed in 1854, but due to the difficulty of the mountainous location the work only started in 1891 and was completed in 1908. This railway, scaling an elevation of 326 m to 2,203 m and still in use today, represented the latest technology of the time. It was highly significant in facilitating population movement and socio-economic development in the British colonial era.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="660" unique="781" trans="0" lat="34.61666667" long="135.73333330">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Nara Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Buddhist Monuments in the Horyu-ji Area</site>
    <description>There are around 48 Buddhist monuments in the Horyu-ji area, in Nara Prefecture. Several date from the late 7th or early 8th century, making them some of the oldest surviving wooden buildings in the world. These masterpieces of wooden architecture are important not only for the history of art, since they illustrate the adaptation of Chinese Buddhist architecture and layout to Japanese culture, but also for the history of religion, since their construction coincided with the introduction of Buddhism to Japan from China by way of the Korean peninsula.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="776" unique="918" trans="0" lat="34.29441667" long="132.32463890">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Hiroshima Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Itsukushima Shinto Shrine</site>
    <description>The island of Itsukushima, in the Seto inland sea, has been a holy place of Shintoism since the earliest times. The first shrine buildings here were probably erected in the 6th century. The present shrine dates from the 12th century and the harmoniously arranged buildings reveal great artistic and technical skill. The shrine plays on the contrasts in colour and form between mountains and sea and illustrates the Japanese concept of scenic beauty, which combines nature and human creativity.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1193" unique="1370" trans="0" lat="43.94944000" long="144.96583000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Hokkaido prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Shiretoko</site>
    <description>Shiretoko Peninsula is located in the north-east of Hokkaido, the northernmost island of Japan. The site includes the land from the central part of the peninsula to its tip (Shiretoko Cape) and the surrounding marine area. It provides an outstanding example of the interaction of marine and terrestrial ecosystems as well as extraordinary ecosystem productivity, largely influenced by the formation of seasonal sea ice at the lowest latitude in the northern hemisphere. It has particular importance for a number of marine and terrestrial species, some of them endangered and endemic, such as Blackiston’s fish owl and the Viola kitamiana plant. The site is globally important for threatened seabirds and migratory birds, a number of salmonid species, and for marine mammals including Steller’s sea lion and some cetacean species.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="143" unique="158" trans="0" lat="24.76666667" long="67.90000000">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>pk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Province of Sind</location>
    <state>Pakistan</state>
    <site>Historical Monuments of Thatta</site>
    <description>The capital of three successive dynasties and later ruled by the Mughal emperors of Delhi, Thatta was constantly embellished from the 14th to the 18th century. The remains of the city and its necropolis provide a unique view of civilization in Sind.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="738" unique="871" trans="0" lat="37.55000000" long="126.98333000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Seoul</location>
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Jongmyo Shrine</site>
    <description>Jongmyo is the oldest and most authentic of the Confucian royal shrines to have been preserved. Dedicated to the forefathers of the Choson dynasty (1392–1910), the shrine has existed in its present form since the 16th century and houses tablets bearing the teachings of members of the former royal family. Ritual ceremonies linking music, song and dance still take place there, perpetuating a tradition that goes back to the 14th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1264" unique="1441" trans="0" lat="33.46888889" long="126.72027778">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location />
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Jeju Volcanic Island and Lava Tubes</site>
    <description>Jeju Volcanic Island and Lava Tubes comprises three sites that together make up 18,846 ha, 10.3% of the surface area of Jeju Island, the southernmost territory of the Republic of Korea. It includes: Geomunoreum, regarded as the finest lave tube system of caves anywhere, with its multi-coloured carbonate roofs and floors, and dark-coloured lava walls; the fortress-like Seongsan Ilchulbong tuff cone, rising out of the ocean, a dramatic landscape; and Mount Hallasan, the highest in Korea, with its waterfalls, multi-shaped rock formations, and lake-filled crater. The property, of outstanding aesthetic beauty, also bears testimony to the history of our planet; to its features and processes.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="138" unique="151" trans="0" lat="27.32916667" long="68.13888889">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1980</inscribeDate>
    <code>pk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Sind</location>
    <state>Pakistan</state>
    <site>Archaeological Ruins at Moenjodaro</site>
    <description>The ruins of the huge city of Moenjodaro – built entirely of unbaked brick in the 3rd millennium B.C. – lie in the Indus valley. The acropolis, set on high embankments, the ramparts, and the lower town, which is laid out according to strict rules, provide evidence of an early system of town planning.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="139" unique="153" trans="0" lat="33.77916667" long="72.88750000">
    <criteria>(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1980</inscribeDate>
    <code>pk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Province of Punjab</location>
    <state>Pakistan</state>
    <site>Taxila</site>
    <description>From the ancient Neolithic tumulus of Saraikala to the ramparts of Sirkap (2nd century B.C.) and the city of Sirsukh (1st century A.D.), Taxila illustrates the different stages in the development of a city on the Indus that was alternately influenced by Persia, Greece and Central Asia and which, from the 5th century B.C. to the 2nd century A.D., was an important Buddhist centre of learning.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="140" unique="154" trans="0" lat="34.32083333" long="71.94583333">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1980</inscribeDate>
    <code>pk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>North West Frontier Province</location>
    <state>Pakistan</state>
    <site>Buddhist Ruins of Takht-i-Bahi and Neighbouring City Remains at Sahr-i-Bahlol</site>
    <description>The Buddhist monastic complex of Takht-i-Bahi (Throne of Origins) was founded in the early 1st century. Owing to its location on the crest of a high hill, it escaped successive invasions and is still exceptionally well preserved. Nearby are the ruins of Sahr-i-Bahlol, a small fortified city dating from the same period.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="171" unique="189" trans="0" lat="31.59027778" long="74.30972222">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>pk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Lahore, Punjab</location>
    <state>Pakistan</state>
    <site>Fort and Shalamar Gardens in Lahore</site>
    <description>These are two masterpieces from the time of the brilliant Mughal civilization, which reached its height during the reign of the Emperor Shah Jahan. The fort contains marble palaces and mosques decorated with mosaics and gilt. The elegance of these splendid gardens, built near the city of Lahore on three terraces with lodges, waterfalls and large ornamental ponds, is unequalled.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="586" unique="693" trans="0" lat="32.96250000" long="73.58888889">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>pk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Jhelum City, Punjab</location>
    <state>Pakistan</state>
    <site>Rohtas Fort</site>
    <description>Following his defeat of the Mughal emperor Humayun in 1541, Sher Shah Suri built a strong fortified complex at Rohtas, a strategic site in the north of what is now Pakistan. It was never taken by storm and has survived intact to the present day. The main fortifications consist of the massive walls, which extend for more than 4 km; they are lined with bastions and pierced by monumental gateways. Rohtas Fort, also called Qila Rohtas, is an exceptional example of early Muslim military architecture in Central and South Asia.</description>
  </row>
  
  <row id="736" unique="869" trans="0" lat="35.78333333" long="129.35000000">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>North Kyongsang Province</location>
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Seokguram Grotto and Bulguksa Temple</site>
    <description>Established in the 8th century on the slopes of Mount T'oham, the Seokguram Grotto contains a monumental statue of the Buddha looking at the sea in the &lt;I&gt;bhumisparsha mudra&lt;/I&gt; position. With the surrounding portrayals of gods, Bodhisattvas and disciples, all realistically and delicately sculpted in high and low relief, it is considered a masterpiece of Buddhist art in the Far East. The Temple of Bulguksa (built in 774) and the Seokguram Grotto form a religious architectural complex of exceptional significance.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="737" unique="870" trans="0" lat="35.80000000" long="128.10000000">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>South Kyongsang Province</location>
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Haeinsa Temple Janggyeong Panjeon, the Depositories for the &lt;I&gt;Tripitaka Koreana&lt;/I&gt; Woodblocks</site>
    <description>The Temple of Haeinsa, on Mount Kaya, is home to the &lt;I&gt;Tripitaka Koreana&lt;/I&gt;, the most complete collection of Buddhist texts, engraved on 80,000 woodblocks between 1237 and 1248. The buildings of Janggyeong Pangeon, which date from the 15th century, were constructed to house the woodblocks, which are also revered as exceptional works of art. As the oldest depository of the &lt;I&gt;Tripitaka&lt;/I&gt;, they reveal an astonishing mastery of the invention and implementation of the conservation techniques used to preserve these woodblocks.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="870" unique="1021" trans="0" lat="34.67555556" long="135.83944440">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Nara Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Historic Monuments of Ancient Nara</site>
    <description>Nara was the capital of Japan from 710 to 784. During this period the framework of national government was consolidated and Nara enjoyed great prosperity, emerging as the fountainhead of Japanese culture. The city's historic monuments – Buddhist temples, Shinto shrines and the excavated remains of the great Imperial Palace – provide a vivid picture of life in the Japanese capital in the 8th century, a period of profound political and cultural change.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="913" unique="1066" trans="0" lat="36.74750000" long="139.61055560">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Tochigi Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Shrines and Temples of Nikko</site>
    <description>The shrines and temples of Nikko, together with their natural surroundings, have for centuries been a sacred site known for its architectural and decorative masterpieces. They are closely associated with the history of the Tokugawa Shoguns.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="972" unique="1136" trans="0" lat="26.20861111" long="127.68277780">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Okinawa Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Gusuku Sites and Related Properties of the Kingdom of Ryukyu</site>
    <description>Five hundred years of Ryukyuan history (12th-17th century) are represented by this group of sites and monuments. The ruins of the castles, on imposing elevated sites, are evidence for the social structure over much of that period, while the sacred sites provide mute testimony to the rare survival of an ancient form of religion into the modern age. The wide- ranging economic and cultural contacts of the Ryukyu Islands over that period gave rise to a unique culture.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1142" unique="1323" trans="0" lat="33.83694444" long="135.77638890">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Mie, Nara and Wakayama Prefectures</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Sacred Sites and Pilgrimage Routes in the Kii Mountain Range</site>
    <description>Set in the dense forests of the Kii Mountains overlooking the Pacific Ocean, three sacred sites – Yoshino and Omine, Kumano Sanzan, Koyasan – linked by pilgrimage routes to the ancient capital cities of Nara and Kyoto, reflect the fusion of Shinto, rooted in the ancient tradition of nature worship in Japan, and Buddhism, which was introduced from China and the Korean Peninsula. The sites (495.3 ha) and their surrounding forest landscape reflect a persistent and extraordinarily well-documented tradition of sacred mountains over 1,200 years. The area, with its abundance of streams, rivers and waterfalls, is still part of the living culture of Japan and is much visited for ritual purposes and hiking, with up to 15 million visitors annually. Each of the three sites contains shrines, some of which were founded as early as the 9th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="816" unique="964" trans="0" lat="37.55000000" long="126.98333330">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Seoul</location>
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Changdeokgung Palace Complex</site>
    <description>In the early 15th century, the Emperor T'aejong ordered the construction of a new palace at an auspicious site. A Bureau of Palace Construction was set up to create the complex, consisting of a number of official and residential buildings set in a garden that was cleverly adapted to the uneven topography of the 58-ha site. The result is an exceptional example of Far Eastern palace architecture and design, blending harmoniously with the surrounding landscape.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="817" unique="965" trans="0" lat="37.27222000" long="127.00833000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kyonggi-do Province</location>
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Hwaseong Fortress</site>
    <description>When the Choson emperor Chongjo moved his father's tomb to Suwon at the end of the 18th century, he surrounded it with strong defensive works, laid out according to the precepts of an influential military architect of the period, who brought together the latest developments in the field from both East and West. The massive walls, extending for nearly 6 km, still survive; they are pierced by four gates and equipped with bastions, artillery towers and other features.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="976" unique="1140" trans="0" lat="35.78889000" long="129.22667000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kyongju City, Kyongsangbuk-do Province</location>
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Gyeongju Historic Areas</site>
    <description>The Gyeongju Historic Areas contain a remarkable concentration of outstanding examples of Korean Buddhist art, in the form of sculptures, reliefs, pagodas, and the remains of temples and palaces from the flowering, in particular between the 7th and 10th centuries, of this form of unique artistic expression.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="977" unique="1141" trans="0" lat="34.96667000" long="126.92917000">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>kr</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Koch’ang-gun County, Chollabuk-do Province; Hwasun-gun County, Chollanam-do Province; Kangwha-gun County, Inch’on Province</location>
    <state>Republic of Korea</state>
    <site>Gochang, Hwasun and Ganghwa Dolmen Sites</site>
    <description>The prehistoric cemeteries at Gochang, Hwasun, and Ganghwa contain many hundreds of examples of dolmens - tombs from the 1st millennium BC constructed of large stone slabs. They form part of the Megalithic culture, found in many parts of the world, but nowhere in such a concentrated form.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="479" unique="558" trans="0" lat="19.88889000" long="102.13333000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>la</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Province of Luang Prabang</location>
    <state>Lao People's Democratic Republic</state>
    <site>Town of Luang Prabang</site>
    <description>Luang Prabang is an outstanding example of the fusion of traditional architecture and Lao urban structures with those built by the European colonial authorities in the 19th and 20th centuries. Its unique, remarkably well-preserved townscape illustrates a key stage in the blending of these two distinct cultural traditions.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="121" unique="1448" trans="0" lat="27.70395000" long="85.30858000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>np</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kathmandu Valley</location>
    <state>Nepal</state>
    <site>Kathmandu Valley</site>
    <description>The cultural heritage of the Kathmandu Valley is illustrated by seven groups of monuments and buildings which display the full range of historic and artistic achievements for which the Kathmandu Valley is world famous. The seven include the Durbar Squares of Hanuman Dhoka (Kathmandu), Patan and Bhaktapur, the Buddhist stupas of Swayambhu and Bauddhanath and the Hindu temples of Pashupati and Changu Narayan.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1081" unique="1259" trans="0" lat="47.55666667" long="102.83138890">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>mn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Orkhon-Kharkorin Region</location>
    <state>Mongolia</state>
    <site>Orkhon Valley Cultural Landscape</site>
    <description>The 121,967-ha Orkhon Valley Cultural Landscape encompasses an extensive area of pastureland on both banks of the Orkhon River and includes numerous archaeological remains dating back to the 6th century. The site also includes Kharkhorum, the 13th- and 14th-century capital of Chingis (Genghis) Khan’s vast Empire. Collectively the remains in the site reflect the symbiotic links between nomadic, pastoral societies and their administrative and religious centres, and the importance of the Orkhon valley in the history of central Asia. The grassland is still grazed by Mongolian nomadic pastoralists.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="113" unique="122" trans="0" lat="32.08330000" long="48.53333333">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Khuzestan</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Tchogha Zanbil</site>
    <description>The ruins of the holy city of the Kingdom of Elam, surrounded by three huge concentric walls, are found at Tchogha Zanbil. Founded c. 1250 B.C., the city remained unfinished after it was invaded by Ashurbanipal, as shown by the thousands of unused bricks left at the site.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="120" unique="132" trans="0" lat="27.96528000" long="86.91306000">
    <criteria>(vii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>np</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Solu-Khumbu District of the Sagarmatha Zone</location>
    <state>Nepal</state>
    <site>Sagarmatha National Park</site>
    <description>Sagarmatha is an exceptional area with dramatic mountains, glaciers and deep valleys, dominated by Mount Everest, the highest peak in the world (8,848 m). Several rare species, such as the snow leopard and the lesser panda, are found in the park. The presence of the Sherpas, with their unique culture, adds further interest to this site.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="284" unique="318" trans="0" lat="27.50000000" long="84.33333000">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>np</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Chitwan District of the Narayani Zone</location>
    <state>Nepal</state>
    <site>Royal Chitwan National Park</site>
    <description>At the foot of the Himalayas, Chitwan is one of the few remaining undisturbed vestiges of the 'Terai' region, which formerly extended over the foothills of India and Nepal. It has a particularly rich flora and fauna. One of the last populations of single-horned Asiatic rhinoceros lives in the park, which is also one of the last refuges of the Bengal tiger.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="666" unique="788" trans="0" lat="27.46889000" long="83.27611000">
    <criteria>(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>np</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Lumbini Zone, Rupandehi District, Western Terai</location>
    <state>Nepal</state>
    <site>Lumbini, the Birthplace of the Lord Buddha</site>
    <description>Siddhartha Gautama, the Lord Buddha, was born in 623 B.C. in the famous gardens of Lumbini, which soon became a place of pilgrimage. Among the pilgrims was the Indian emperor Ashoka, who erected one of his commemorative pillars there. The site is now being developed as a Buddhist pilgrimage centre, where the archaeological remains associated with the birth of the Lord Buddha form a central feature.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1246" unique="1423" trans="0" lat="35.11277778" long="132.43500000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Shimane Prefecture, Ohda City District</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Iwami Ginzan Silver Mine and its Cultural Landscape</site>
    <description>The Iwami Ginzan Silver Mine, south-west of Honshu Island, is a cluster of mountains, rising to 600 metres and interspersed by deep river valleys featuring the archaeological remains of large-scale mines, smelting and refining sites and mining settlements worked between the 16th and 20th centuries. The site also features transportation routes used to transport silver ore to the coast, and port towns from where it was shipped to Korea and China. The high quality of the silver resulting from the use of advanced techniques, and the quantity of silver mined, contributed substantially to the overall economic development of Japan and southeast Asia in the 16&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 17th centuries, and prompted the mass production of silver and gold in Japan. The mining area is now heavily wooded. Included in the site are fortresses, shrines, parts of &lt;em&gt;Kaidô &lt;/em&gt;transportation routes to the coast and three port towns, Tomogaura, Okidomari and Yunotsu, from where the ore was shipped. The property extends to 442 ha and the buffer zone 3,221 ha.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="481" unique="560" trans="0" lat="14.83333000" long="105.80000000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2001</inscribeDate>
    <code>la</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Champasak Province</location>
    <state>Lao People's Democratic Republic</state>
    <site>Vat Phou and Associated Ancient Settlements within the Champasak Cultural Landscape</site>
    <description>The Champasak cultural landscape, including the Vat Phou Temple complex, is a remarkably well-preserved planned landscape more than 1,000 years old. It was shaped to express the Hindu vision of the relationship between nature and humanity, using an axis from mountain top to river bank to lay out a geometric pattern of temples, shrines and waterworks extending over some 10 km. Two planned cities on the banks of the Mekong River are also part of the site, as well as Phou Kao mountain. The whole represents a development ranging from the 5th to 15th centuries, mainly associated with the Khmer Empire.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="661" unique="782" trans="0" lat="34.83333333" long="134.70000000">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Hyogo Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Himeji-jo</site>
    <description>Himeji-jo is the finest surviving example of early 17th-century Japanese castle architecture, comprising 83 buildings with highly developed systems of defence and ingenious protection devices dating from the beginning of the Shogun period. It is a masterpiece of construction in wood, combining function with aesthetic appeal, both in its elegant appearance unified by the white plastered earthen walls and in the subtlety of the relationships between the building masses and the multiple roof layers.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="662" unique="783" trans="0" lat="30.33333333" long="130.53333330">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kamiyaku-cho and Yaku-cho, Kumage-gun Kagoshima Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Yakushima</site>
    <description>Located in the interior of Yaku Island, at the meeting-point of the palaearctic and oriental biotic regions, Yakushima exhibits a rich flora, with some 1,900 species and subspecies, including ancient specimens of the sugi (Japanese cedar). It also contains a remnant of a warm-temperate ancient forest that is unique in this region.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="663" unique="784" trans="0" lat="40.47000000" long="140.13000000">
    <criteria>(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Ajigasawa-machi, Nishitsugaru-gun, Aomori Prefecture; Fukaura-machi, Nishitsugaru-gun, Aomori Prefecture; Iwasaki-mura, Nishitsugaru-gun, Aomori Prefecture; Fujisato-machi, Yamamoto-gun, Akita Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Shirakami-Sanchi</site>
    <description>Situated in the mountains of northern Honshu, this trackless site includes the last virgin remains of the cool-temperate forest of Siebold's beech trees that once covered the hills and mountain slopes of northern Japan. The black bear, the serow and 87 species of birds can be found in this forest.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="688" unique="814" trans="0" lat="34.98055556" long="135.76944440">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kyoto and Shiga prefectures</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Historic Monuments of Ancient Kyoto (Kyoto, Uji and Otsu Cities)</site>
    <description>Built in A.D. 794 on the model of the capitals of ancient China, Kyoto was the imperial capital of Japan from its foundation until the middle of the 19th century. As the centre of Japanese culture for more than 1,000 years, Kyoto illustrates the development of Japanese wooden architecture, particularly religious architecture, and the art of Japanese gardens, which has influenced landscape gardening the world over.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="734" unique="868" trans="0" lat="36.40000000" long="136.88333330">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Gifu and Toyama prefectures</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Historic Villages of Shirakawa-go and Gokayama</site>
    <description>Located in a mountainous region that was cut off from the rest of the world for a long period of time, these villages with their Gassho-style houses subsisted on the cultivation of mulberry trees and the rearing of silkworms. The large houses with their steeply pitched thatched roofs are the only examples of their kind in Japan. Despite economic upheavals, the villages of Ogimachi, Ainokura and Suganuma are outstanding examples of a traditional way of life perfectly adapted to the environment and people's social and economic circumstances.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="775" unique="917" trans="0" lat="34.38333333" long="132.45000000">
    <criteria>(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>jp</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Hiroshima Prefecture</location>
    <state>Japan</state>
    <site>Hiroshima Peace Memorial (Genbaku Dome)</site>
    <description>The Hiroshima Peace Memorial (Genbaku Dome) was the only structure left standing in the area where the first atomic bomb exploded on 6 August 1945. Through the efforts of many people, including those of the city of Hiroshima, it has been preserved in the same state as immediately after the bombing. Not only is it a stark and powerful symbol of the most destructive force ever created by humankind; it also expresses the hope for world peace and the ultimate elimination of all nuclear weapons.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="232" unique="258" trans="0" lat="28.59333000" long="77.25056000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Delhi</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Humayun's Tomb, Delhi</site>
    <description>This tomb, built in 1570, is of particular cultural significance as it was the first garden-tomb on the Indian subcontinent. It inspired several major architectural innovations, culminating in the construction of the Taj Mahal.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="233" unique="259" trans="0" lat="28.52583000" long="77.18528000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Delhi</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Qutb Minar and its Monuments, Delhi</site>
    <description>Built in the early 13th century a few kilometres south of Delhi, the red sandstone tower of Qutb Minar is 72.5 m high, tapering from 2.75 m in diameter at its peak to 14.32 m at its base, and alternating angular and rounded flutings. The surrounding archaeological area contains funerary buildings, notably the magnificent Alai-Darwaza Gate, the masterpiece of Indo-Muslim art (built in 1311), and two mosques, including the Quwwatu'l-Islam, the oldest in northern India, built of materials reused from some 20 Brahman temples.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="234" unique="260" trans="0" lat="15.50222000" long="73.91167000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1986</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Goa</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Churches and Convents of Goa</site>
    <description>The churches and convents of Goa, the former capital of the Portuguese Indies – particularly the Church of Bom Jesus, which contains the tomb of St Francis-Xavier – illustrate the evangelization of Asia. These monuments were influential in spreading forms of Manueline, Mannerist and Baroque art in all the countries of Asia where missions were established.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="335" unique="382" trans="0" lat="30.71667000" long="79.66667000">
    <criteria>(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Uttaranchal</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Nanda Devi and Valley of Flowers National Parks</site>
    <description>Nestled high in West Himalaya, India’s Valley of Flowers National Park is renowned for its meadows of endemic alpine flowers and outstanding natural beauty. This richly diverse area is also home to rare and endangered animals, including the Asiatic black bear, snow leopard, brown bear and blue sheep. The gentle landscape of the Valley of Flowers National Park complements the rugged mountain wilderness of Nanda Devi National Park. Together they encompass a unique transition zone between the mountain ranges of the Zanskar and Great Himalaya, praised by mountaineers and botanists for over a century and in Hindu mythology for much longer.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="337" unique="384" trans="0" lat="26.66666667" long="93.41666667">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Assam</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Kaziranga National Park</site>
    <description>In the heart of Assam, this park is one of the last areas in eastern India undisturbed by a human presence. It is inhabited by the world's largest population of one-horned rhinoceroses, as well as many mammals, including tigers, elephants, panthers and bears, and thousands of birds.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="338" unique="385" trans="0" lat="26.72500000" long="91.03055556">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Assam</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Manas Wildlife Sanctuary</site>
    <description>On a gentle slope in the foothills of the Himalayas, where wooded hills give way to alluvial grasslands and tropical forests, the Manas sanctuary is home to a great variety of wildlife, including many endangered species, such as the tiger, pygmy hog, Indian rhinoceros and Indian elephant.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="340" unique="387" trans="0" lat="27.15888889" long="77.50861111">
    <criteria>(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Rajasthan, 50 km west of Agra</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Keoladeo National Park</site>
    <description>This former duck-hunting reserve of the Maharajas is one of the major wintering areas for large numbers of aquatic birds from Afghanistan, Turkmenistan, China and Siberia. Some 364 species of birds, including the rare Siberian crane, have been recorded in the park.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="452" unique="524" trans="0" lat="21.94500000" long="88.89583333">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>West Bengal</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Sundarbans National Park</site>
    <description>The Sundarbans covers 10,000  km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of land and water (more than half of it in India, the rest in Bangladesh) in the Ganges delta. It contains the world's largest area of mangrove forests. A number of rare or endangered species live in the park, including tigers, aquatic mammals, birds and reptiles.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="524" unique="613" trans="0" lat="23.47944000" long="77.73972000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1989</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Madhya Pradesh</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Buddhist Monuments at Sanchi</site>
    <description>On a hill overlooking the plain and about 40 km from Bhopal, the site of Sanchi comprises a group of Buddhist monuments (monolithic pillars, palaces, temples and monasteries) all in different states of conservation most of which date back to the 2nd and 1st centuries B.C. It is the oldest Buddhist sanctuary in existence and was a major Buddhist centre in India until the 12th century A.D.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="925" unique="1079" trans="0" lat="22.92777778" long="77.58333333">
    <criteria>(iii)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Madhya Pradesh</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Rock Shelters of Bhimbetka</site>
    <description>The Rock Shelters of Bhimbetka are in the foothills of the Vindhyan Mountains on the southern edge of the central Indian plateau. Within massive sandstone outcrops, above comparatively dense forest, are five clusters of natural rock shelters, displaying paintings that appear to date from the Mesolithic Period right through to the historical period. The cultural traditions of the inhabitants of the twenty-one villages adjacent to the site bear a strong resemblance to those represented in the rock paintings.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="945" unique="1105" trans="0" lat="18.94012222" long="72.83620278">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>City of Mumbai, Maharashtra State</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus (formerly Victoria Terminus)</site>
    <description>The Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus, formerly known as Victoria Terminus Station, in Mumbai, is an outstanding example of Victorian Gothic Revival architecture in India, blended with themes deriving from Indian traditional architecture. The building, designed by the British architect F. W. Stevens, became the symbol of Bombay as the ‘Gothic City’ and the major international mercantile port of India. The terminal was built over 10 years, starting in 1878, according to a High Victorian Gothic design based on late medieval Italian models. Its remarkable stone dome, turrets, pointed arches and eccentric ground plan are close to traditional Indian palace architecture. It is an outstanding example of the meeting of two cultures, as British architects worked with Indian craftsmen to include Indian architectural tradition and idioms thus forging a new style unique to Bombay.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1056" unique="1231" trans="0" lat="24.69528000" long="84.99389000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2002</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Bihar, Eastern India</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Mahabodhi Temple Complex at Bodh Gaya</site>
    <description>The Mahabodhi Temple Complex is one of the four holy sites related to the life of the Lord Buddha, and particularly to the attainment of Enlightenment. The first temple was built by Emperor Asoka in the 3rd century B.C., and the present temple dates from the 5th or 6th centuries. It is one of the earliest Buddhist temples built entirely in brick, still standing in India, from the late Gupta period.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1101" unique="1279" trans="0" lat="22.48333333" long="73.53333333">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(v)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Gujarat state, district of Panchmahal</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Champaner-Pavagadh Archaeological Park</site>
    <description>A concentration of largely unexcavated archaeological, historic and living cultural heritage properties cradled in an impressive landscape which includes prehistoric (chalcolithic) sites, a hill fortress of an early Hindu capital, and remains of the 16th-century capital of the state of Gujarat. The site also includes, among other vestiges, fortifications, palaces, religious buildings, residential precincts, agricultural structures and water installations, from the 8th to 14th centuries. The Kalikamata Temple on top of Pavagadh Hill is considered to be an important shrine, attracting large numbers of pilgrims throughout the year. The site is the only complete and unchanged Islamic pre-Mughal city.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1103" unique="1281" trans="0" lat="43.29305556" long="68.27444444">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>kz</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>South Kazakhstan Oblast, City of Turkestan</location>
    <state>Kazakhstan</state>
    <site>Mausoleum of Khoja Ahmed Yasawi</site>
    <description>The Mausoleum of Khoja Ahmed Yasawi, in the town of Yasi, now Turkestan, was built at the time of Timur (Tamerlane), from 1389 to 1405. In this partly unfinished building, Persian master builders experimented with architectural and structural solutions later used in the construction of Samarkand, the capital of the Timurid Empire. Today, it is one of the largest and best-preserved constructions of the Timurid period.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1145" unique="1326" trans="0" lat="43.80333333" long="75.53500000">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>kz</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Almaty Oblast</location>
    <state>Kazakhstan</state>
    <site>Petroglyphs within the Archaeological Landscape of Tamgaly</site>
    <description>Set around the lush Tamgaly Gorge, amidst the vast, arid Chu-Ili mountains, is a remarkable concentration of some 5,000 petroglyphs (rock carvings) dating from the second half of the second millennium BC to the beginning of the 20th century. Distributed among 48 complexes with associated settlements and burial grounds, they are testimonies to the husbandry, social organization and rituals of pastoral peoples. Human settlements in the site are often multilayered and show occupation through the ages. A huge number of ancient tombs are also to be found including stone enclosures with boxes and cists (middle and late Bronze Age), and mounds (kurgans) of stone and earth (early Iron Age to the present). The central canyon contains the densest concentration of engravings and what are believed to be altars, suggesting that these places were used for sacrificial offerings.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="911" unique="1064" trans="0" lat="27.71667000" long="117.68333000">
    <criteria>(iii)(vi)(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Wuyishan City, Fujian Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mount Wuyi</site>
    <description>Mount Wuyi is the most outstanding area for biodiversity conservation in south-east China and a refuge for a large number of ancient, relict species, many of them endemic to China. The serene beauty of the dramatic gorges of the Nine Bend River, with its numerous temples and monasteries, many now in ruins, provided the setting for the development and spread of neo-Confucianism, which has been influential in the cultures of East Asia since the 11th century. In the 1st century B.C. a large administrative capital was built at nearby Chengcun by the Han dynasty rulers. Its massive walls enclose an archaeological site of great significance.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="912" unique="1065" trans="0" lat="29.70111000" long="105.70500000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Dazu County, Chongqing Municipality</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Dazu Rock Carvings</site>
    <description>The steep hillsides of the Dazu area contain an exceptional series of rock carvings dating from the 9th to the 13th century. They are remarkable for their aesthetic quality, their rich diversity of subject matter, both secular and religious, and the light that they shed on everyday life in China during this period. They provide outstanding evidence of the harmonious synthesis of Buddhism, Taoism and Confucianism.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1001" unique="1167" trans="0" lat="31.00167000" long="103.60528000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Dujiangyan City, Sichuan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mount Qingcheng and the Dujiangyan Irrigation System</site>
    <description>Construction of the Dujiangyan irrigation system began in the 3rd century B.C. This system still controls the waters of the Minjiang River and distributes it to the fertile farmland of the Chengdu plains. Mount Qingcheng was the birthplace of Taoism, which is celebrated in a series of ancient temples.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1002" unique="1168" trans="0" lat="29.90444444" long="117.98750000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Yi county, Huangshan city, Anhui Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Ancient Villages in Southern Anhui – Xidi and Hongcun</site>
    <description>The two traditional villages of Xidi and Hongcun preserve to a remarkable extent the appearance of non-urban settlements of a type that largely disappeared or was transformed during the last century. Their street plan, their architecture and decoration, and the integration of houses with comprehensive water systems are unique surviving examples.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1003" unique="1169" trans="0" lat="34.46666667" long="112.46666670">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Luoyang City, Henan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Longmen Grottoes</site>
    <description>The grottoes and niches of Longmen contain the largest and most impressive collection of Chinese art of the late Northern Wei and Tang Dynasties (316-907). These works, entirely devoted to the Buddhist religion, represent the high point of Chinese stone carving.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="239" unique="266" trans="0" lat="15.94833000" long="75.81667000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Karnataka, Bijapur District, Badami Taluk</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Group of Monuments at Pattadakal</site>
    <description>Pattadakal, in Karnataka, represents the high point of an eclectic art which, in the 7th and 8th centuries under the Chalukya dynasty, achieved a harmonious blend of architectural forms from northern and southern India. An impressive series of nine Hindu temples, as well as a Jain sanctuary, can be seen there. One masterpiece from the group stands out – the Temple of Virupaksha, built c. 740 by Queen Lokamahadevi to commemorate her husband's victory over the kings from the South.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="250" unique="280" trans="0" lat="10.78305556" long="79.13250000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location />
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Great Living Chola Temples</site>
    <description>The Great Living Chola Temples were built by kings of the Chola Empire, which stretched over all of south India and the neighbouring islands. The site includes three great 11th- and 12th-century Temples: the Brihadisvara Temple at Thanjavur, the Brihadisvara Temple at Gangaikondacholisvaram and the Airavatesvara Temple at Darasuram. The Temple of Gangaikondacholisvaram, built by Rajendra I, was completed in 1035. Its 53-m &lt;em&gt;vimana&lt;/em&gt; (sanctum tower) has recessed corners and a graceful upward curving movement, contrasting with the straight and severe tower at Thanjavur. The Airavatesvara temple complex, built by Rajaraja II, at Darasuram features a 24-m &lt;em&gt;vimana&lt;/em&gt; and a stone image of Shiva. The temples testify to the brilliant achievements of the Chola in architecture, sculpture, painting and bronze casting.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="251" unique="281" trans="0" lat="27.18333333" long="78.03333333">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Uttar Pradesh, Agra District</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Agra Fort</site>
    <description>Near the gardens of the Taj Mahal stands the important 16th-century Mughal monument known as the Red Fort of Agra. This powerful fortress of red sandstone encompasses, within its 2.5-km-long enclosure walls, the imperial city of the Mughal rulers. It comprises many fairy-tale palaces, such as the Jahangir Palace and the Khas Mahal, built by Shah Jahan; audience halls, such as the Diwan-i-Khas; and two very beautiful mosques.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="252" unique="282" trans="0" lat="27.17417000" long="78.04222000">
    <criteria>(i)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Uttar Pradesh, Agra District</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Taj Mahal</site>
    <description>An immense mausoleum of white marble, built in Agra between 1631 and 1648 by order of the Mughal emperor Shah Jahan in memory of his favourite wife, the Taj Mahal is the jewel of Muslim art in India and one of the universally admired masterpieces of the world's heritage.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="240" unique="267" trans="0" lat="24.85222000" long="79.92222000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1986</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Madhya Pradesh</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Khajuraho Group of Monuments</site>
    <description>The temples at Khajuraho were built during the Chandella dynasty, which reached its apogee between 950 and 1050. Only about 20 temples remain; they fall into three distinct groups and belong to two different religions – Hinduism and Jainism. They strike a perfect balance between architecture and sculpture. The Temple of Kandariya is decorated with a profusion of sculptures that are among the greatest masterpieces of Indian art.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="241" unique="268" trans="0" lat="15.31444000" long="76.47167000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1986</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Karnataka, Bellary District</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Group of Monuments at Hampi</site>
    <description>The austere, grandiose site of Hampi was the last capital of the last great Hindu Kingdom of Vijayanagar. Its fabulously rich princes built Dravidian temples and palaces which won the admiration of travellers between the 14th and 16th centuries. Conquered by the Deccan Muslim confederacy in 1565, the city was pillaged over a period of six months before being abandoned.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="242" unique="269" trans="0" lat="20.55333000" long="75.70000000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Maharashtra State, Aurangabad District , Soyagon Taluka, Lenapur Village</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Ajanta Caves</site>
    <description>The first Buddhist cave monuments at Ajanta date from the 2nd and 1st centuries B.C. During the Gupta period (5th and 6th centuries A.D.), many more richly decorated caves were added to the original group. The paintings and sculptures of Ajanta, considered masterpieces of Buddhist religious art, have had a considerable artistic influence.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="243" unique="270" trans="0" lat="20.02639000" long="75.17917000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Maharashtra State, Aurangabad District, Khulatabad Taluk , Verul Village</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Ellora Caves</site>
    <description>These 34 monasteries and temples, extending over more than 2 km, were dug side by side in the wall of a high basalt cliff, not far from Aurangabad, in Maharashtra. Ellora, with its uninterrupted sequence of monuments dating from A.D. 600 to 1000, brings the civilization of ancient India to life. Not only is the Ellora complex a unique artistic creation and a technological exploit but, with its sanctuaries devoted to Buddhism, Hinduism and Jainism, it illustrates the spirit of tolerance that was characteristic of ancient India.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="244" unique="272" trans="0" lat="18.96667000" long="72.93583000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Maharashtra State, District Kolaba (Island of Elephanta)</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Elephanta Caves</site>
    <description>The 'City of Caves', on an island in the Sea of Oman close to Bombay, contains a collection of rock art linked to the cult of Shiva. Here, Indian art has found one of its most perfect expressions, particularly the huge high reliefs in the main cave.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="246" unique="274" trans="0" lat="19.88750000" long="86.09472000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>State of Orissa, Puri District</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Sun Temple, Konârak</site>
    <description>On the shores of the Bay of Bengal, bathed in the rays of the rising sun, the temple at Konarak is a monumental representation of the sun god Surya's chariot; its 24 wheels are decorated with symbolic designs and it is led by a team of six horses. Built in the 13th century, it is one of India's most famous Brahman sanctuaries.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="249" unique="277" trans="0" lat="12.61667000" long="80.19167000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Tamil Nadu State, Chingleput District</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Group of Monuments at Mahabalipuram</site>
    <description>This group of sanctuaries, founded by the Pallava kings, was carved out of rock along the Coromandel coast in the 7th and 8th centuries. It is known especially for its &lt;I&gt;rathas&lt;/I&gt; (temples in the form of chariots), &lt;I&gt;mandapas&lt;/I&gt; (cave sanctuaries), giant open-air reliefs such as the famous 'Descent of the Ganges', and the temple of Rivage, with thousands of sculptures to the glory of Shiva.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1106" unique="1284" trans="0" lat="30.19383000" long="53.16729000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Pars Province</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Pasargadae</site>
    <description>Pasargadae was the first dynastic capital of the Achaemenid Empire, founded by Cyrus II the Great, in Pars, homeland of the Persians, in the 6th century BC. Its palaces, gardens and the mausoleum of Cyrus are outstanding examples of the first phase of royal Achaemenid art and architecture and exceptional testimonies of Persian civilization. Particularly noteworthy vestiges in the 160-ha site include: the Mausoleum of Cyrus II; Tall-e Takht, a fortified terrace; and a royal ensemble of gatehouse, audience hall, residential palace and gardens. Pasargadae was the capital of the first great multicultural empire in Western Asia. Spanning the Eastern Mediterranean and Egypt to the Hindus River, it is considered to be the first empire that respected the cultural diversity of its different peoples. This was reflected in Achaemenid architecture, a synthetic representation of different cultures.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1188" unique="1365" trans="0" lat="36.43528000" long="48.79667000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Zanjan province</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Soltaniyeh</site>
    <description>The mausoleum of Oljaytu was constructed in 1302–12 in the city of Soltaniyeh, the capital of the Ilkhanid dynasty, which was founded by the Mongols. Situated in the province of Zanjan, Soltaniyeh is one of the outstanding examples of the achievements of Persian architecture and a key monument in the development of its Islamic architecture. The octagonal building is crowned with a 50 m tall dome covered in turquoise-blue faience and surrounded by eight slender minarets. It is the earliest existing example of the double-shelled dome in Iran. The mausoleum’s interior decoration is also outstanding and scholars such as A.U. Pope have described the building as ‘anticipating the Taj Mahal’.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1222" unique="1399" trans="0" lat="34.38833333" long="47.43666667">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2006</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Province of Kermanshah</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Bisotun</site>
    <description>Bisotun is located along the ancient trade route linking the Iranian high plateau with Mesopotamia and features remains from the prehistoric times to the Median, Achaemenid, Sassanian, and Ilkhanid periods. The principal monument of this archaeological site is the bas-relief and cuneiform inscription ordered by Darius I, The Great, when he rose to the throne of the Persian Empire, 521 BC. The bas-relief portrays Darius holding a bow, as a sign of sovereignty, and treading on the chest of a figure who lies on his back before him. According to legend, the figure represents Gaumata, the Median Magus and pretender to the throne whose assassination led to Darius’s rise to power. Below and around the bas-reliefs, there are ca. 1,200 lines of inscriptions telling the story of the battles Darius waged in 521-520 BC against the governors who attempted to take apart the Empire founded by Cyrus. The inscription is written in three languages. The oldest is an Elamite text referring to legends describing the king and the rebellions. This is followed by a Babylonian version of similar legends. The last phase of the inscription is particularly important, as it is here that Darius introduced for the first time the Old Persian version of his res gestae (things done). This is the only known monumental text of the Achaemenids to document the re-establishment of the Empire by Darius I. It also bears witness to the interchange of influences in the development of monumental art and writing in the region of the Persian Empire. There are also remains from the Median period (8th to 7th centuries B.C.) as well as from the Achaemenid (6th to 4th centuries B.C.) and post-Achaemenid periods.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="231" unique="1460" trans="0" lat="28.65555556" long="77.24083333">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>in</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>New Delhi State, Central District, New Delhi</location>
    <state>India</state>
    <site>Red Fort Complex</site>
    <description>The Red Fort Complex was built as the palace fort of Shahjahanabad - the new capital of the 5th Mughal Emperor of India, Shahjahan (1628-58). It gets its name from its massive enclosing walls of red sandstone. It is adjacent to an older fort, the Salimgarh, built by Islam Shah Sur in 1546, with which it forms the Red Fort Complex. The private apartments consist of a row of pavilions connected by a continuous water channel, known as the &lt;em&gt;Nahr-i-Behisht&lt;/em&gt;, or the Stream of Paradise. The palace was designed as an imitation of paradise as described in the Koran; a couplet inscribed in the palace reads, ‘If there be a paradise on earth, it is here, it is here&amp;#39;. The Red Fort is considered to represent the zenith of Mughal creativity which, under the Emperor Shahjahan, was brought to a new level of refinement. The planning of the palace is based on Islamic prototypes, but each pavilion reveals architectural elements typical of Mughal building, reflecting a fusion of Persian, Timurid and Hindu traditions The Red Fort&amp;#39;s innovative planning and architectural style, including its garden design, strongly influenced later buildings and gardens in Rajasthan, Delhi, Agra and further afield. The monument&amp;#39;s significance is further enhanced by the importance of events that happened. Through its fabric, the complex reflects all phases of Indian history from the Mughal period to independence.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="114" unique="123" trans="0" lat="29.93444000" long="52.89028000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Fars</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Persepolis</site>
    <description>Founded by Darius I in 518 B.C., Persepolis was the capital of the Achaemenid Empire. It was built on an immense half-artificial, half-natural terrace, where the king of kings created an impressive palace complex inspired by Mesopotamian models. The importance and quality of the monumental ruins make it a unique archaeological site.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="115" unique="125" trans="0" lat="32.65745000" long="51.67777778">
    <criteria>(i)(v)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Esfahan</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Meidan Emam, Esfahan</site>
    <description>Built by Shah Abbas I the Great at the beginning of the 17th century, and bordered on all sides by monumental buildings linked by a series of two-storeyed arcades, the site is known for the Royal Mosque, the Mosque of Sheykh Lotfollah, the magnificent Portico of Qaysariyyeh and the 15th-century Timurid palace. They are an impressive testimony to the level of social and cultural life in Persia during the Safavid era.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1077" unique="1254" trans="0" lat="36.60388889" long="47.23500000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Western Azerbaijan Province</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Takht-e Soleyman</site>
    <description>The archaeological site of Takht-e Soleyman, in north-western Iran, is situated in a valley set in a volcanic mountain region. The site includes the principal Zoroastrian sanctuary partly rebuilt in the Ilkhanid (Mongol) period (13th century) as well as a temple of the Sasanian period (6th and 7th centuries) dedicated to Anahita. The site has important symbolic significance. The designs of the fire temple, the palace and the general layout have strongly influenced the development of Islamic architecture.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1208" unique="1564" trans="0" lat="29.11683000" long="58.36666667">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>ir</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kerman Province, Bam District</location>
    <state>Iran (Islamic Republic of)</state>
    <site>Bam and its Cultural Landscape</site>
    <description>Bam is situated in a desert environment on the southern edge of the Iranian high plateau. The origins of Bam can be traced back to the Achaemenid period (6th to 4th centuries BC). Its heyday was from the 7th to 11th centuries, being at the crossroads of important trade routes and known for the production of silk and cotton garments. The existence of life in the oasis was based on the underground irrigation canals, the qanats, of which Bam has preserved some of the earliest evidence in Iran. Arg-e Bam is the most representative example of a fortified medieval town built in vernacular technique using mud layers (&lt;em&gt;Chineh&lt;/em&gt;).</description>
  </row>
  <row id="321" unique="365" trans="0" lat="22.66667000" long="89.80000000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>bd</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Khulna District</location>
    <state>Bangladesh</state>
    <site>Historic Mosque City of Bagerhat</site>
    <description>Situated in the suburbs of Bagerhat, at the meeting-point of the Ganges and Brahmaputra rivers, this ancient city, formerly known as Khalifatabad, was founded by the Turkish general Ulugh Khan Jahan in the 15th century. The city’s infrastructure reveals considerable technical skill and an exceptional number of mosques and early Islamic monuments, many built of brick, can be seen there.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="322" unique="366" trans="0" lat="25.03333333" long="88.98333333">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>bd</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Naogaon Subdivision of Rajshahi District</location>
    <state>Bangladesh</state>
    <site>Ruins of the Buddhist Vihara at Paharpur</site>
    <description>Evidence of the rise of Mahayana Buddhism in Bengal from the 7th century onwards, Somapura Mahavira, or the Great Monastery, was a renowned intellectual centre until the 12th century. Its layout perfectly adapted to its religious function, this monastery-city represents a unique artistic achievement. With its simple, harmonious lines and its profusion of carved decoration, it influenced Buddhist architecture as far away as Cambodia.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="798" unique="943" trans="0" lat="21.95000000" long="89.18333000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>bd</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>South-Western Region (Khulna Division)</location>
    <state>Bangladesh</state>
    <site>The Sundarbans</site>
    <description>The Sundarbans mangrove forest, one of the largest such forests in the world (140,000 ha), lies on the delta of the Ganges, Brahmaputra and Meghna rivers on the Bay of Bengal. It is adjacent to the border of India’s Sundarbans World Heritage site inscribed in 1987. The site is intersected by a complex network of tidal waterways, mudflats and small islands of salt-tolerant mangrove forests, and presents an excellent example of ongoing ecological processes. The area is known for its wide range of fauna, including 260 bird species, the Bengal tiger and other threatened species such as the estuarine crocodile and the Indian python.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="437" unique="507" trans="0" lat="36.26667000" long="117.10000000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(v)(vi)(vii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Spanning the cities of Tai’an and Jinan in central Shandong Province with the main peak in the city of Tai’an</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mount Taishan</site>
    <description>The sacred Mount Tai ('shan' means 'mountain') was the object of an imperial cult for nearly 2,000 years, and the artistic masterpieces found there are in perfect harmony with the natural landscape. It has always been a source of inspiration for Chinese artists and scholars and symbolizes ancient Chinese civilizations and beliefs.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="438" unique="508" trans="0" lat="40.41667000" long="116.08333000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Liaoning, Jilin, Hebei, Beijing, Tianjin, Shanxi, Inner Mongolia, Shaanxi, Ningxia, Gansu, Xinjiang, Shandong, Henan, Hubei, Hunan, Sichuan, Qinghai provinces, municipalities and autonomous Regions</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>The Great Wall</site>
    <description>In c. 220 B.C., under Qin Shi Huang, sections of earlier fortifications were joined together to form a united defence system against invasions from the north. Construction continued up to the Ming dynasty (1368–1644), when the Great Wall became the world's largest military structure. Its historic and strategic importance is matched only by its architectural significance.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="440" unique="511" trans="0" lat="40.13333000" long="94.81667000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(v)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Dunhuang County, Gansu Province.  At the eastern foot of Mount Mingsha, 25 kilometres southeast of the County seat.</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mogao Caves</site>
    <description>Situated at a strategic point along the Silk Route, at the crossroads of trade as well as religious, cultural and intellectual influences, the 492 cells and cave sanctuaries in Mogao are famous for their statues and wall paintings, spanning 1,000 years of Buddhist art.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="441" unique="512" trans="0" lat="34.38333333" long="109.10000000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Lintong County, Shaanxi Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mausoleum of the First Qin Emperor</site>
    <description>No doubt thousands of statues still remain to be unearthed at this archaeological site, which was not discovered until 1974. Qin (d. 210 B.C.), the first unifier of China, is buried, surrounded by the famous terracotta warriors, at the centre of a complex designed to mirror the urban plan of the capital, Xianyan. The small figures are all different; with their horses, chariots and weapons, they are masterpieces of realism and also of great historical interest.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="449" unique="521" trans="0" lat="39.73333333" long="115.91666670">
    <criteria>(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Fangshanxian County, Beijing Municipality</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Peking Man Site at Zhoukoudian</site>
    <description>Scientific work at the site, which lies 42 km south-west of Beijing, is still underway. So far, it has led to the discovery of the remains of &lt;I&gt;Sinanthropus pekinensis&lt;/I&gt;, who lived in the Middle Pleistocene, along with various objects, and remains of &lt;I&gt;Homo sapiens sapiens&lt;/I&gt; dating as far back as 18,000–11,000 B.C. The site is not only an exceptional reminder of the prehistorical human societies of the Asian continent, but also illustrates the process of evolution.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="547" unique="643" trans="0" lat="30.16667000" long="118.18333000">
    <criteria>(ii)(vii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1990</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>City of Huangshan, Anhui Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mount Huangshan</site>
    <description>Huangshan, known as 'the loveliest mountain of China', was acclaimed through art and literature during a good part of Chinese history (e.g. the Shanshui 'mountain and water' style of the mid-16th century). Today it holds the same fascination for visitors, poets, painters and photographers who come on pilgrimage to the site, which is renowned for its magnificent scenery made up of many granite peaks and rocks emerging out of a sea of clouds.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="637" unique="757" trans="0" lat="33.08333000" long="103.91667000">
    <criteria>(vii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Nanping County, Sichuan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Jiuzhaigou Valley Scenic and Historic Interest Area</site>
    <description>Stretching over 72,000 ha in the northern part of Sichuan Province, the jagged Jiuzhaigou valley reaches a height of more than 4,800 m, thus comprising a series of diverse forest ecosystems. Its superb landscapes are particularly interesting for their series of narrow conic karst land forms and spectacular waterfalls. Some 140 bird species also inhabit the valley, as well as a number of endangered plant and animal species, including the giant panda and the Sichuan takin.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="638" unique="758" trans="0" lat="32.75417000" long="103.82222000">
    <criteria>(vii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Songpan County, Sichuan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Huanglong Scenic and Historic Interest Area</site>
    <description>Situated in the north-west of Sichaun Province, the Huanglong valley is made up of snow-capped peaks and the easternmost of all the Chinese glaciers. In addition to its mountain landscape, diverse forest ecosystems can be found, as well as spectacular limestone formations, waterfalls and hot springs. The area also has a population of endangered animals, including the giant panda and the Sichuan golden snub-nosed monkey.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="703" unique="831" trans="0" lat="40.98694000" long="117.93833000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Chengde City, Hebei Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mountain Resort and its Outlying Temples, Chengde</site>
    <description>The Mountain Resort (the Qing dynasty's summer palace), in Hebei Province, was built between 1703 and 1792. It is a vast complex of palaces and administrative and ceremonial buildings. Temples of various architectural styles and imperial gardens blend harmoniously into a landscape of lakes, pastureland and forests. In addition to its aesthetic interest, the Mountain Resort is a rare historic vestige of the final development of feudal society in China.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="704" unique="832" trans="0" lat="35.61167000" long="116.97500000">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Qufu City, Shandong Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Temple and Cemetery of Confucius and the Kong Family Mansion in Qufu</site>
    <description>The temple, cemetery and family mansion of Confucius, the great philosopher, politician and educator of the 6th–5th centuries B.C., are located at Qufu, in Shandong Province. Built to commemorate him in 478 B.C., the temple has been destroyed and reconstructed over the centuries; today it comprises more than 100 buildings. The cemetery contains Confucius' tomb and the remains of more than 100,000 of his descendants. The small house of the Kong family developed into a gigantic aristocratic residence, of which 152 buildings remain. The Qufu complex of monuments has retained its outstanding artistic and historic character due to the devotion of successive Chinese emperors over more than 2,000 years.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="705" unique="833" trans="0" lat="32.46667000" long="111.00000000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Danjiangkou City, Hubei Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Ancient Building Complex in the Wudang Mountains</site>
    <description>The palaces and temples which form the nucleus of this group of secular and religious buildings exemplify the architectural and artistic achievements of China's Yuan, Ming and Qing dynasties. Situated in the scenic valleys and on the slopes of the Wudang mountains in Hubei Province, the site, which was built as an organized complex during the Ming dynasty (14th–17th centuries), contains Taoist buildings from as early as the 7th century. It represents the highest standards of Chinese art and architecture over a period of nearly 1,000 years.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="778" unique="921" trans="0" lat="29.43333333" long="115.86666670">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Jiujiang City,  Jiangxi Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Lushan National Park</site>
    <description>Mount Lushan, in Jiangxi, is one of the spiritual centres of Chinese civilization. Buddhist and Taoist temples, along with landmarks of Confucianism, where the most eminent masters taught, blend effortlessly into a strikingly beautiful landscape which has inspired countless artists who developed the aesthetic approach to nature found in Chinese culture.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="779" unique="922" trans="0" lat="29.54490000" long="103.76925000">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1996</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Eimeishan City, Sichuan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Mount Emei Scenic Area, including Leshan Giant Buddha Scenic Area</site>
    <description>The first Buddhist temple in China was built here in Sichuan Province in the 1st century A.D. in the beautiful surroundings of the summit Mount Emei. The addition of other temples turned the site into one of Buddhism&amp;#39;s holiest sites. Over the centuries, the cultural treasures grew in number. The most remarkable is the Giant Buddha of Leshan, carved out of a hillside in the 8th century and looking down on the confluence of three rivers. At 71 m high, it is the largest Buddha in the world. Mount Emei is also notable for its exceptionally diverse vegetation, ranging from subtropical to subalpine pine forests. Some of the trees there are more than 1,000 years old.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="811" unique="958" trans="0" lat="26.86667000" long="100.23333000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Lijiang's old town  (including the Dayan old town, Basha housing cluster and Shuhe housing cluster)</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Old Town of Lijiang</site>
    <description>The Old Town of Lijiang, which is perfectly adapted to the uneven topography of this key commercial and strategic site, has retained a historic townscape of high quality and authenticity. Its architecture is noteworthy for the blending of elements from several cultures that have come together over many centuries. Lijiang also possesses an ancient water-supply system of great complexity and ingenuity that still functions effectively today.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="812" unique="959" trans="0" lat="37.20139000" long="112.15444000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Ping Yao County, Shan Xi Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Ancient City of Ping Yao</site>
    <description>Ping Yao is an exceptionally well-preserved example of a traditional Han Chinese city, founded in the 14th century. Its urban fabric shows the evolution of architectural styles and town planning in Imperial China over five centuries. Of special interest are the imposing buildings associated with banking, for which Ping Yao was the major centre for the whole of China in the 19th and early 20th centuries.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="813" unique="961" trans="0" lat="31.31666667" long="120.45000000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1997</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Suzhou City, Jiangsu Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Classical Gardens of Suzhou</site>
    <description>Classical Chinese garden design, which seeks to recreate natural landscapes in miniature, is nowhere better illustrated than in the nine gardens in the historic city of Suzhou. They are generally acknowledged to be masterpieces of the genre. Dating from the 11th-19th century, the gardens reflect the profound metaphysical importance of natural beauty in Chinese culture in their meticulous design.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="880" unique="1032" trans="0" lat="39.91055556" long="116.14111110">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1998</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>10 km northwest of Beijing</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Summer Palace, an Imperial Garden in Beijing</site>
    <description>The Summer Palace in Beijing – first built in 1750, largely destroyed in the war of 1860 and restored on its original foundations in 1886 – is a masterpiece of Chinese landscape garden design. The natural landscape of hills and open water is combined with artificial features such as pavilions, halls, palaces, temples and bridges to form a harmonious ensemble of outstanding aesthetic value.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="200" unique="221" trans="0" lat="8.33333333" long="80.38333333">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>lk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>North Central Province, Anuradhapura District</location>
    <state>Sri Lanka</state>
    <site>Sacred City of Anuradhapura</site>
    <description>This sacred city was established around a cutting from the 'tree of enlightenment', the Buddha's fig tree, brought there in the 3rd century B.C. by Sanghamitta, the founder of an order of Buddhist nuns. Anuradhapura, a Ceylonese political and religious capital that flourished for 1,300 years, was abandoned after an invasion in 993. Hidden away in dense jungle for many years, the splendid site, with its palaces, monasteries and monuments, is now accessible once again.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="201" unique="222" trans="0" lat="7.91583333" long="81.00055556">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>lk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>North Central Province, Polonnaruva District</location>
    <state>Sri Lanka</state>
    <site>Ancient City of Polonnaruwa</site>
    <description>Polonnaruwa was the second capital of Sri Lanka after the destruction of Anuradhapura in 993. It comprises, besides the Brahmanic monuments built by the Cholas, the monumental ruins of the fabulous garden-city created by Parakramabahu I in the 12th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="202" unique="223" trans="0" lat="7.95000000" long="80.75000000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>lk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Central Province,  Matale District</location>
    <state>Sri Lanka</state>
    <site>Ancient City of Sigiriya</site>
    <description>The ruins of the capital built by the parricidal King Kassapa I (477–95) lie on the steep slopes and at the summit of a granite peak standing some 370 m high (the 'Lion's Rock', which dominates the jungle from all sides). A series of galleries and staircases emerging from the mouth of a gigantic lion constructed of bricks and plaster provide access to the site.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="405" unique="468" trans="0" lat="6.41666667" long="80.50000000">
    <criteria>(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>lk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Sabaragamuwa and Southern Provinces</location>
    <state>Sri Lanka</state>
    <site>Sinharaja Forest Reserve</site>
    <description>Located in south-west Sri Lanka, Sinharaja is the country's last viable area of primary tropical rainforest. More than 60% of the trees are endemic and many of them are considered rare. There is much endemic wildlife, especially birds, but the reserve is also home to over 50% of Sri Lanka's endemic species of mammals and butterflies, as well as many kinds of insects, reptiles and rare amphibians.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="450" unique="522" trans="0" lat="7.29361111" long="80.64027778">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>lk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Central Province</location>
    <state>Sri Lanka</state>
    <site>Sacred City of Kandy</site>
    <description>This sacred Buddhist site, popularly known as the city of Senkadagalapura, was the last capital of the Sinhala kings whose patronage enabled the Dinahala culture to flourish for more than 2,500 years until the occupation of Sri Lanka by the British in 1815. It is also the site of the Temple of the Tooth Relic (the sacred tooth of the Buddha), which is a famous pilgrimage site.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="451" unique="523" trans="0" lat="6.02138889" long="80.21861111">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1988</inscribeDate>
    <code>lk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>City of Galle, Southern Province</location>
    <state>Sri Lanka</state>
    <site>Old Town of Galle and its Fortifications</site>
    <description>Founded in the 16th century by the Portuguese, Galle reached the height of its development in the 18th century, before the arrival of the British. It is the best example of a fortified city built by Europeans in South and South-East Asia, showing the interaction between European architectural styles and South Asian traditions.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="561" unique="663" trans="0" lat="7.85666667" long="80.64916667">
    <criteria>(i)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>lk</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Central Province, Matale District</location>
    <state>Sri Lanka</state>
    <site>Golden Temple of Dambulla</site>
    <description>A sacred pilgrimage site for 22 centuries, this cave monastery, with its five sanctuaries, is the largest, best-preserved cave-temple complex in Sri Lanka. The Buddhist mural paintings (covering an area of 2,100 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) are of particular importance, as are the 157 statues.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="574" unique="679" trans="0" lat="17.00722000" long="99.78972000">
    <criteria>(i)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>th</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Sukhothai and Kamphaeng Phet Provinces</location>
    <state>Thailand</state>
    <site>Historic Town of Sukhothai and Associated Historic Towns</site>
    <description>Sukhothai was the capital of the first Kingdom of Siam in the 13th and 14th centuries. It has a number of fine monuments, illustrating the beginnings of Thai architecture. The great civilization which evolved in the Kingdom of Sukhothai absorbed numerous influences and ancient local traditions; the rapid assimilation of all these elements forged what is known as the &amp;#39;Sukhothai style&amp;#39;.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="575" unique="680" trans="0" lat="17.54861000" long="103.35833000">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>th</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Udon Thani Province</location>
    <state>Thailand</state>
    <site>Ban Chiang Archaeological Site</site>
    <description>Ban Chiang is considered the most important prehistoric settlement so far discovered in South-East Asia. It marks an important stage in human cultural, social and technological evolution. The site presents the earliest evidence of farming in the region and of the manufacture and use of metals.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="576" unique="681" trans="0" lat="14.34778000" long="100.56056000">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>th</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Ayutthaya Province</location>
    <state>Thailand</state>
    <site>Historic City of Ayutthaya</site>
    <description>Founded c. 1350, Ayutthaya became the second Siamese capital after Sukhothai. It was destroyed by the Burmese in the 18th century. Its remains, characterized by the prang (reliquary towers) and gigantic monasteries, give an idea of its past splendour.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="590" unique="698" trans="0" lat="14.33000000" long="102.05000000">
    <criteria>(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>th</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Provinces of Saraburi, Nakhon Nayok, Nakhon Rachisima, Prachinburi, Srakaew and Burirum</location>
    <state>Thailand</state>
    <site>Dong Phayayen-Khao Yai Forest Complex</site>
    <description>The Dong Phayayen-Khao Yai Forest Complex spans 230 km between Ta Phraya National Park on the Cambodian border in the east, and Khao Yai National Park in the west. The site is home to more than 800 species of fauna, including 112 mammal species (among them two species of gibbon), 392 bird species and 200 reptile and amphibian species. It is internationally important for the conservation of globally threatened and endangered mammal, bird and reptile species, among them 19 that are vulnerable, four that are endangered, and one that is critically endangered. The area contains substantial and important tropical forest ecosystems, which can provide a viable habitat for the long-term survival of these species.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="591" unique="699" trans="0" lat="15.33333000" long="98.91667000">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1991</inscribeDate>
    <code>th</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kanchanaburi, Tak and Uthai Thani provinces</location>
    <state>Thailand</state>
    <site>Thungyai-Huai Kha Khaeng Wildlife Sanctuaries</site>
    <description>Stretching over more than 600,000 ha along the Myanmar border, the sanctuaries, which are relatively intact, contain examples of almost all the forest types of continental South-East Asia. They are home to a very diverse array of animals, including 77% of the large mammals (especially elephants and tigers), 50% of the large birds and 33% of the land vertebrates to be found in this region.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="886" unique="1038" trans="0" lat="37.70083000" long="62.17750000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>tm</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Mary Vilayet</location>
    <state>Turkmenistan</state>
    <site>State Historical and Cultural Park 'Ancient Merv'</site>
    <description>Merv is the oldest and best-preserved of the oasis-cities along the Silk Route in Central Asia. The remains in this vast oasis span 4,000 years of human history. A number of monuments are still visible, particularly from the last two millennia.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1199" unique="1376" trans="0" lat="42.18318000" long="59.08494000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>tm</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Dashoguz Vilayet (Province)</location>
    <state>Turkmenistan</state>
    <site>Kunya-Urgench</site>
    <description>Kunya-Urgench is situated in north-western Turkmenistan, on the left bank of the Amu Daria River. Urgench was the capital of the Khorezm region, part of the Achaemenid Empire. The old town contains a series of monuments mainly from the 11th to 16th centuries, including a mosque, the gates of a caravanserai, fortresses, mausoleums and a 60-m high minaret. The monuments testify to outstanding achievements in architecture and craftsmanship whose influence reached Iran and Afghanistan, and later the architecture of the Mogul Empire of 16th-century India.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1242" unique="1471" trans="0" lat="37.99972222" long="58.19861111">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>tm</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Bagyr settlement, Etrap of Rukhabad, Akhal Vilayet</location>
    <state>Turkmenistan</state>
    <site>Parthian Fortresses of Nisa</site>
    <description>Parthian Fortresses of Nisa consists of two tells of Old and New Nisa which indicate the site of one of the earliest and most important cities of the Parthian Empire, was a major power from the mid 3rd century BC to the 3rd century AD. They have been relatively undisturbed for nearly two millennia and conserve the unexcavated remains of an ancient civilization which skilfully combined its own traditional cultural elements with those of the Hellenistic and Roman west. Archaeological excavations in two parts of the site have revealed richly decorated architecture, illustrative of domestic, state, and religious functions. Most of the excavation to date has been carried out at the Royal citadel, now known as Old Nisa, but the site also includes the ancient town, known as New Nisa. Old Nisa is a 14-ha tell shaped like an irregular pentagon and surrounded by a high defensive earth rampart with more than 40 rectangular towers, its corners flanked by powerful bastions. The 25-ha tell of New Nisa is surrounded by powerful walls, up to 9m high on all sides, with two entrances. Situated at the crossroads of important commercial and strategic axes, the archaeological remains of Nisa vividly illustrate the significant interaction of cultural influences from central Asia and the Mediterranean in this powerful empire which formed a barrier to Roman expansion while serving as an important communication and trading centre between east and west, north and south. The site testifies to the significance of this imperial power, to its wealth and culture.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="543" unique="638" trans="0" lat="41.37833000" long="60.36389000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1990</inscribeDate>
    <code>uz</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Khorezm region, Khiva</location>
    <state>Uzbekistan</state>
    <site>Itchan Kala</site>
    <description>Itchan Kala is the inner town (protected by brick walls some 10 m high) of the old Khiva oasis, which was the last resting-place of caravans before crossing the desert to Iran. Although few very old monuments still remain, it is a coherent and well-preserved example of the Muslim architecture of Central Asia. There are several outstanding structures such as the Djuma Mosque, the mausoleums and the madrasas and the two magnificent palaces built at the beginning of the 19th century by Alla-Kulli-Khan.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="602" unique="713" trans="0" lat="39.77472000" long="64.42861000">
    <criteria>(ii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>uz</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Bukhara region</location>
    <state>Uzbekistan</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Bukhara</site>
    <description>Bukhara, which is situated on the Silk Route, is more than 2,000 years old. It is the most complete example of a medieval city in Central Asia, with an urban fabric that has remained largely intact. Monuments of particular interest include the famous tomb of Ismail Samani, a masterpiece of 10th-century Muslim architecture, and a large number of 17th-century madrasas.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="603" unique="715" trans="0" lat="39.66861000" long="67.00000000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2001</inscribeDate>
    <code>uz</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Samarkand Region</location>
    <state>Uzbekistan</state>
    <site>Samarkand  – Crossroads of Cultures</site>
    <description>The historic town of Samarkand is a crossroad and melting pot of the world's cultures. Founded in the 7th century B.C. as ancient Afrasiab, Samarkand had its most significant development in the Timurid period from the 14th to the 15th centuries. The major monuments include the Registan Mosque and madrasas, Bibi-Khanum Mosque, the Shakhi-Zinda compound and the Gur-Emir ensemble, as well as Ulugh-Beg's Observatory.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="885" unique="1037" trans="0" lat="39.05000000" long="66.83333000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2000</inscribeDate>
    <code>uz</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Kashkadarya region</location>
    <state>Uzbekistan</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Shakhrisyabz</site>
    <description>The historic centre of Shakhrisyabz contains a collection of exceptional monuments and ancient quarters which bear witness to the city's secular development, and particularly to the period of its apogee, under the rule of Amir Temur and the Temurids, in the 15th-16th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="672" unique="796" trans="0" lat="20.90000000" long="107.10000000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1994</inscribeDate>
    <code>vn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Province: Quang Ninh</location>
    <state>Viet Nam</state>
    <site>Ha Long Bay</site>
    <description>Ha Long Bay, in the Gulf of Tonkin, includes some 1,600 islands and islets, forming a spectacular seascape of limestone pillars. Because of their precipitous nature, most of the islands are uninhabited and unaffected by a human presence. The site&amp;#39;s outstanding scenic beauty is complemented by its great biological interest.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="678" unique="802" trans="0" lat="16.46944000" long="107.57778000">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1993</inscribeDate>
    <code>vn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Province: Thua Thien - Hue</location>
    <state>Viet Nam</state>
    <site>Complex of Hué Monuments</site>
    <description>Established as the capital of unified Viet Nam in 1802, Hué was not only the political but also the cultural and religious centre under the Nguyen dynasty until 1945. The Perfume River winds its way through the Capital City, the Imperial City, the Forbidden Purple City and the Inner City, giving this unique feudal capital a setting of great natural beauty.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="948" unique="1109" trans="0" lat="15.88333333" long="108.33333330">
    <criteria>(ii)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>vn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Hoi An Town, Quang Nam Province</location>
    <state>Viet Nam</state>
    <site>Hoi An Ancient Town</site>
    <description>Hoi An Ancient Town is an exceptionally well-preserved example of a South-East Asian trading port dating from the 15th to the 19th century. Its buildings and its street plan reflect the influences, both indigenous and foreign, that have combined to produce this unique heritage site.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="949" unique="1110" trans="0" lat="15.51666667" long="108.56666670">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>vn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Duy Phu Commune, Duy Xuyen District, Quang Nam Province</location>
    <state>Viet Nam</state>
    <site>My Son Sanctuary</site>
    <description>Between the 4th and 13th centuries a unique culture which owed its spiritual origins to Indian Hinduism developed on the coast of contemporary Viet Nam. This is graphically illustrated by the remains of a series of impressive tower-temples located in a dramatic site that was the religious and political capital of the Champa Kingdom for most of its existence.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="951" unique="1113" trans="0" lat="17.53722222" long="106.15125000">
    <criteria>(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>vn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Bo Trach and Minh Hoa Districts - Quang Binh Province</location>
    <state>Viet Nam</state>
    <site>Phong Nha-Ke Bang National Park</site>
    <description>The karst formation of Phong Nha-Ke Bang National Park has evolved since the Palaeozoic (some 400 million years ago) and so is the oldest major karst area in Asia. Subject to massive tectonic changes, the park’s karst landscape is extremely complex with many geomorphic features of considerable significance. The vast area, extending to the border of the Lao People’s Democratic Republic, contains spectacular formations including 65 km of caves and underground rivers.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1039" unique="1213" trans="0" lat="40.10972000" long="113.12222000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2001</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Datong City, Shanxi Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Yungang Grottoes</site>
    <description>The Yungang Grottoes, in Datong city, Shanxi Province, with their 252 caves and 51,000 statues, represent the outstanding achievement of Buddhist cave art in China in the 5th and 6th centuries. The Five Caves created by Tan Yao, with their strict unity of layout and design, constitute a classical masterpiece of the first peak of Chinese Buddhist art.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1083" unique="1261" trans="0" lat="27.89500000" long="98.40638889">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Lijiang Prefecture, Diqing Tibetan Autonomous Prefecture and Nujiang Lisu Autonomous Prefecture, Yunnan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Three Parallel Rivers of Yunnan Protected Areas</site>
    <description>Consisting of eight geographical clusters of protected areas within the boundaries of the Three Parallel Rivers National Park, in the mountainous north-west of Yunnan Province, the 1.7 million hectare site features sections of the upper reaches of three of the great rivers of Asia: the Yangtze (Jinsha), Mekong and Salween run roughly parallel, north to south, through steep gorges which, in places, are 3,000 m deep and are bordered by glaciated peaks more than 6,000 m high. The site is an epicentre of Chinese biodiversity. It is also one of the richest temperate regions of the world in terms of biodiversity.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1110" unique="1289" trans="0" lat="22.19129194" long="113.53646111">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2005</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Macao Special Administrative Region</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Historic Centre of Macao</site>
    <description>Macao, a lucrative port of strategic importance in the development of international trade, was under Portuguese administration from the mid-16th century until 1999, when it came under Chinese sovereignty. With its historic street, residential, religious and public Portuguese and Chinese buildings, the historic centre of Macao provides a unique testimony to the meeting of aesthetic, cultural, architectural and technological influences from East and West. The site also contains a fortress and a lighthouse, the oldest in China. It bears witness to one of the earliest and longest-lasting encounters between China and the West, based on the vibrancy of international trade.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="208" unique="230" trans="0" lat="34.84694000" long="67.82525000">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2003</inscribeDate>
    <code>af</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Bamiyan Province, Bamiyan District</location>
    <state>Afghanistan</state>
    <site>Cultural Landscape and Archaeological Remains of the Bamiyan Valley</site>
    <description>The cultural landscape and archaeological remains of the Bamiyan Valley represent the artistic and religious developments which from the 1st to the 13th centuries characterized ancient Bakhtria, integrating various cultural influences into the Gandhara school of Buddhist art. The area contains numerous Buddhist monastic ensembles and sanctuaries, as well as fortified edifices from the Islamic period. The site is also testimony to the tragic destruction by the Taliban of the two standing Buddha statues, which shook the world in March 2001.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="211" unique="234" trans="0" lat="34.39655556" long="64.51605556">
    <criteria>(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2002</inscribeDate>
    <code>af</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Shahrak District, Ghur Province</location>
    <state>Afghanistan</state>
    <site>Minaret and Archaeological Remains of Jam</site>
    <description>The 65m-tall Minaret of Jam is a graceful, soaring structure, dating back to the 12th century. Covered in elaborate brickwork with a blue tile inscription at the top, it is noteworthy for the quality of its architecture and decoration, which represent the culmination of an architectural and artistic tradition in this region. Its impact is heightened by its dramatic setting, a deep river valley between towering mountains in the heart of the Ghur province.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1135" unique="1315" trans="0" lat="41.15694444" long="126.18722220">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2004</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Huanren County, Liaoning Province and Ji’an, Jilin Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Capital Cities and Tombs of the Ancient Koguryo Kingdom</site>
    <description>The site includes archaeological remains of three cities and 40 tombs: Wunu Mountain City, Guonei City and Wandu Mountain City, 14 tombs are imperial, 26 of nobles. All belong to the Koguryo culture, named after the dynasty that ruled over parts of northern China and the northern half of the Korean Peninsula from 277 BC to AD 668. Wunu Mountain City is only partly excavated. Guonei City, within the modern city of Ji’an, played the role of a ‘supporting capital’ after the main Koguryo capital moved to Pyongyang. Wandu Mountain City, one of the capitals of the Koguryo Kingdom, contains many vestiges including a large palace and 37 tombs. Some of the tombs show great ingenuity in their elaborate ceilings, designed to roof wide spaces without columns and carry the heavy load of a stone or earth tumulus (mound), which was placed above them.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1213" unique="1390" trans="0" lat="30.83333333" long="103.00000000">
    <criteria>(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2006</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Sichuan Province</location>
    <state>China</state>
    <site>Sichuan Giant Panda Sanctuaries</site>
    <description>Sichuan Giant Panda Sanctuaries, home to more than 30% of the world's pandas which are classed as highly endangered, covers 924,500 ha with seven nature reserves and nine scenic parks in the Qionglai and Jiajin Mountains. The sanctuaries constitute the largest remaining contiguous habitat of the giant panda, a relict from the paleo-tropic forests of the Tertiary Era. It is also the species' most important site for captive breeding. The sanctuaries are home to other globally endangered animals such as the red panda, the snow leopard and clouded leopard. They are among the botanically richest sites of any region in the world outside the tropical rainforests, with between 5,000 and 6,000 species of flora in over 1,000 genera.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1248" unique="1425" trans="0" lat="25.22083333" long="107.97500000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>cn</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location />
    <state>China</state>
    <site>South China Karst</site>
    <description>The South China Karst region extends over a surface of half a million square kilometres lying mainly in Yunnan, Guizhou and Guangxi Provinces. South China is unrivalled for the diversity of its karst features and landscapes. The site presents a coherent serial property comprising three clusters: Libo Karst, Shilin Karst and Wulong Karst. South China Karst represents one of the world&amp;#39;s most spectacular examples of humid tropical to sub-tropical karst landscapes. The stone forests of Shilin are considered superlative natural phenomena and a world reference. The cluster includes the Naigu stone forest occurring on dolomitic limestone and the Suyishan stone forest arising from a lake. Shilin contains a wider range of pinnacle shapes than other karst landscapes with pinnacles, and a higher diversity of shapes and changing colours. The cone and tower karsts of Libo, also considered the world reference site for these types of karsts, form a distinctive and beautiful landscape. Wulong Karst has been inscribed for its giant dolines, natural bridges and caves.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="668" unique="791" trans="0" lat="13.43333333" long="103.83333330">
    <criteria>(i)(ii)(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>kh</code>
    <region>Asia</region>
    <location>Province Siem Reap</location>
    <state>Cambodia</state>
    <site>Angkor</site>
    <description>Angkor is one of the most important archaeological sites in South-East Asia. Stretching over some 400 km2, including forested area, Angkor Archaeological Park contains the magnificent remains of the different capitals of the Khmer Empire, from the 9th to the 15th century. They include the famous Temple of Angkor Wat and, at Angkor Thom, the Bayon Temple with its countless sculptural decorations. UNESCO has set up a wide-ranging programme to safeguard this symbolic site and its surroundings.</description>
  </row>
</worldheritage>