<worldheritage promo="UNESCO">
<row id="27" unique="30" trans="0" lat="37.26166667" long="-108.48555560">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1978</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Colorado</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Mesa Verde National Park</site>
    <description>A great concentration of ancestral Pueblo Indian dwellings, built from the 6th to the 12th century, can be found on the Mesa Verde plateau in south-west Colorado at an altitude of more than 2,600 m. Some 4,400 sites have been recorded, including villages built on the Mesa top. There are also imposing cliff dwellings, built of stone and comprising more than 100 rooms.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="28" unique="31" trans="0" lat="44.46056000" long="-110.82778000">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1978</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Northwest corner of the State of Wyoming and relatively small adjacent areas of the States of Montana and Idaho</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Yellowstone National Park</site>
    <description>The vast natural forest of Yellowstone National Park covers nearly 9,000 sq. km; 96% of the park lies in Wyoming, 3% in Montana and 1% in Idaho. Yellowstone contains half of all the world's known geothermal features, with more than 10,000 examples. It also has the world's largest concentration of geysers (more than 300 geyers, or 2/3 of all those on the planet). Established in 1872, Yellowstone is equally known for its wildlife, such as grizzly bears, wolves, bison and wapitis.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="75" unique="81" trans="0" lat="36.10083333" long="-112.09055560">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Counties of Coconino and Mohave in the State of Arizona</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Grand Canyon National Park</site>
    <description>Carved out by the Colorado river, the Grand Canyon (nearly 1,500 m deep) is the most spectacular gorge in the world. Located in the state of Arizona, it cuts across the Grand Canyon National Park. Its horizontal strata retrace the geological history of the past 2 billion years. There are also prehistoric traces of human adaptation to a particularly harsh environment.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="76" unique="82" trans="0" lat="25.55444444" long="-80.99638889">
    <criteria>(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Southern tip of the Florida peninsula, along the Gulf of Mexico, State of Florida</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Everglades National Park</site>
    <description>This site at the southern tip of Florida has been called &amp;#39;a river of grass flowing imperceptibly from the hinterland into the sea&amp;#39;. The exceptional variety of its water habitats has made it a sanctuary for a large number of birds and reptiles, as well as for threatened species such as the manatee.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="78" unique="84" trans="0" lat="39.94861111" long="-75.15000000">
    <criteria>(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Philadelphia, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Independence Hall</site>
    <description>The Declaration of Independence (1776) and the Constitution of the United States (1787) were both signed in this building in Philadelphia. The universal principles of freedom and democracy set forth in these documents are of fundamental importance to American history and have also had a profound impact on law-makers around the world.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="134" unique="147" trans="0" lat="41.37388889" long="-123.99805560">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1980</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>California</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Redwood National and State Parks</site>
    <description>Redwood National Park comprises a region of coastal mountains bordering the Pacific Ocean north of San Francisco. It is covered with a magnificent forest of sequoia redwood trees, the tallest and most impressive trees in the world. The marine and land life are equally remarkable, in particular the sea lions, the bald eagle and the endangered California brown pelican.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="150" unique="168" trans="0" lat="37.18722222" long="-86.10305556">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Counties of Barren, Edmonson, and Hart in the State of Kentucky</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Mammoth Cave National Park</site>
    <description>Mammoth Cave National Park, located in the state of Kentucky, has the world's largest network of natural caves and underground passageways, which are characteristic examples of limestone formations. The park and its underground network of more than 560 surveyed km of passageways are home to a varied flora and fauna, including a number of endangered species.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="151" unique="169" trans="0" lat="47.74833333" long="-123.44888890">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>State of Washington</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Olympic National Park</site>
    <description>Located in the north-west of Washington State, Olympic National Park is renowned for the diversity of its ecosystems. Glacier-clad peaks interspersed with extensive alpine meadows are surrounded by an extensive old growth forest, among which is the best example of intact and protected temperate rainforest in the Pacific Northwest. Eleven major river systems drain the Olympic mountains, offering some of the best habitat for anadromous fish species in the country. The park also includes 100 km of wilderness coastline, the longest undeveloped coast in the contiguous United States, and is rich in native and endemic animal and plant species, including critical populations of the endangered northern spotted owl, marbled murrelet and bull trout.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="198" unique="219" trans="0" lat="38.65861111" long="-90.06138889">
    <criteria>(iii)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1982</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>St. Louis, Illinois</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site</site>
    <description>Cahokia Mounds, some 13 km north-east of St Louis, Missouri, is the largest pre-Columbian settlement north of Mexico. It was occupied primarily during the Mississippian period (800–1400), when it covered nearly 1,600 ha and included some 120 mounds. It is a striking example of a complex chiefdom society, with many satellite mound centres and numerous outlying hamlets and villages. This agricultural society may have had a population of 10–20,000 at its peak between 1050 and 1150. Primary features at the site include Monks Mound, the largest prehistoric earthwork in the Americas, covering over 5 ha and standing 30 m high.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="259" unique="289" trans="0" lat="35.59305556" long="-83.43555556">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Counties of Cocke, Blount, and Sevier in the State of Tennessee; and the counties of Swain and Haywood in the state of North Carolina</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Great Smoky Mountains National Park</site>
    <description>Stretching over more than 200,000 ha, this exceptionally beautiful park is home to more than 3,500 plant species, including almost as many trees (130 natural species) as in all of Europe. Many endangered animal species are also found there, including what is probably the greatest variety of salamanders in the world. Since the park is relatively untouched, it gives an idea of temperate flora before the influence of humankind.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="266" unique="296" trans="0" lat="18.46666667" long="-66.12500000">
    <criteria>(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>San Juan, Puerto Rico</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>La Fortaleza and San Juan National Historic Site in Puerto Rico</site>
    <description>Between the 15th and 19th centuries, a series of defensive structures was built at this strategic point in the Caribbean Sea to protect the city and the Bay of San Juan. They represent a fine display of European military architecture adapted to harbour sites on the American continent.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="307" unique="346" trans="0" lat="40.68944444" long="-74.04472222">
    <criteria>(i)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>New York, New York</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Statue of Liberty</site>
    <description>Made in Paris by the French sculptor Bartholdi, in collaboration with Gustave Eiffel (who was responsible for the steel framework), this towering monument to liberty was a gift from France on the centenary of American independence in 1886. Standing at the entrance to New York Harbour, it has welcomed millions of immigrants to the United States ever since.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="308" unique="347" trans="0" lat="37.74611111" long="-119.59666670">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>California</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Yosemite National Park</site>
    <description>Yosemite National Park lies in the heart of California. With its &amp;#39;hanging&amp;#39; valleys, many waterfalls, cirque lakes, polished domes, moraines and U-shaped valleys, it provides an excellent overview of all kinds of granite relief fashioned by glaciation. At 600–4,000 m, a great variety of flora and fauna can also be found here.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="353" unique="405" trans="0" lat="36.06377778" long="-107.97083330">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>New Mexico</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Chaco Culture</site>
    <description>For over 2,000 years, Pueblo peoples occupied a vast region of the south-western United States. Chaco Canyon, a major centre of ancestral Pueblo culture between 850 and 1250, was a focus for ceremonials, trade and political activity for the prehistoric Four Corners area. Chaco is remarkable for its monumental public and ceremonial buildings and its distinctive architecture – it has an ancient urban ceremonial centre that is unlike anything constructed before or since. In addition to the Chaco Culture National Historical Park, the World Heritage property includes the Aztec Ruins National Monument and several smaller Chaco sites managed by the Bureau of Land Management.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="409" unique="472" trans="0" lat="19.40083333" long="-155.12361110">
    <criteria>(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Hawaii</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Hawaii Volcanoes National Park</site>
    <description>This site contains two of the most active volcanoes in the world, Mauna Loa (4,170 m high) and Kilauea (1,250 m high), both of which tower over the Pacific Ocean. Volcanic eruptions have created a constantly changing landscape, and the lava flows reveal surprising geological formations. Rare birds and endemic species can be found there, as well as forests of giant ferns.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="442" unique="513" trans="0" lat="38.03277778" long="-78.50388889">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Virginia</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Monticello and the University of Virginia in Charlottesville</site>
    <description>Thomas Jefferson (1743–1826), author of the American Declaration of Independence and third president of the United States, was also a talented architect of neoclassical buildings.  He designed Monticello (1769–1809), his plantation home, and his ideal 'academical village' (1817–26), which is still the heart of the University of Virginia.  Jefferson's use of an architectural vocabulary based upon classical antiquity symbolizes both the aspirations of the new American republic as the inheritor of European tradition and the cultural experimentation that could be expected as the country matured.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="492" unique="573" trans="0" lat="36.43889000" long="-105.54167000">
    <criteria>(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1992</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>New Mexico</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Pueblo de Taos</site>
    <description>Situated in the valley of a small tributary of the Rio Grande, this adobe settlement – consisting of dwellings and ceremonial buildings – represents the culture of the Pueblo Indians of Arizona and New Mexico.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="721" unique="852" trans="0" lat="32.16666667" long="-104.38333330">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Eddy County, State of New Mexico</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Carlsbad Caverns National Park</site>
    <description>This karst landscape in the state of New Mexico comprises over 80 recognized caves. They are outstanding not only for their size but also for the profusion, diversity and beauty of their mineral formations. Lechuguilla Cave stands out from the others, providing an underground laboratory where geological and biological processes can be studied in a pristine setting.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="72" unique="78" trans="1" lat="61.19758333" long="-140.99197220">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Glacier Bay:  Alaska (USA)</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Kluane / Wrangell-St Elias / Glacier Bay / Tatshenshini-Alsek</site>
    <description>These parks comprise an impressive complex of glaciers and high peaks on both sides of the border between Canada (Yukon Territory and British Columbia) and the United States (Alaska). The spectacular natural landscapes are home to many grizzly bears, caribou and Dall's sheep. The site contains the largest non-polar icefield in the world.</description>
  </row>
   <row id="72" unique="78" trans="1" lat="61.19758333" long="-140.99197220">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Kluane: Yukon Territory (Canada) and Tatshenshini:  Province of British Columbia (Canada)</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Kluane / Wrangell-St Elias / Glacier Bay / Tatshenshini-Alsek</site>
    <description>These parks comprise an impressive complex of glaciers and high peaks on both sides of the border between Canada (Yukon Territory and British Columbia) and the United States (Alaska). The spectacular natural landscapes are home to many grizzly bears, caribou and Dall's sheep. The site contains the largest non-polar icefield in the world.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="354" unique="407" trans="1" lat="48.99605556" long="-113.90416670">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>us</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>State of Montana, USA</location>
    <state>United States of America</state>
    <site>Waterton Glacier International Peace Park</site>
    <description>In 1932 Waterton Lakes National Park (Alberta, Canada) was combined with the Glacier National Park (Montana, United States) to form the world&amp;#39;s first International Peace Park. Situated on the border between the two countries and offering outstanding scenery, the park is exceptionally rich in plant and mammal species as well as prairie, forest, and alpine and glacial features.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="354" unique="407" trans="1" lat="48.99605556" long="-113.90416670">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Province of Alberta, Canada</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Waterton Glacier International Peace Park</site>
    <description>In 1932 Waterton Lakes National Park (Alberta, Canada) was combined with the Glacier National Park (Montana, United States) to form the world&amp;#39;s first International Peace Park. Situated on the border between the two countries and offering outstanding scenery, the park is exceptionally rich in plant and mammal species as well as prairie, forest, and alpine and glacial features.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="157" unique="175" trans="0" lat="52.09500000" long="-131.22027780">
    <criteria>(iii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Province of British Columbia</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>SGang Gwaay</site>
    <description>The village of Ninstints (Nans Dins) is located on a small island off the west coast of the Queen Charlotte Islands (Haida Gwaii). Remains of houses, together with carved mortuary and memorial poles, illustrate the Haida people's art and way of life. The site commemorates the living culture of the Haida people and their relationship to the land and sea, and offers a visual key to their oral traditions.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="741" unique="875" trans="0" lat="44.37611111" long="-64.30916667">
    <criteria>(iv)(v)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1995</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Nova Scotia</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Old Town Lunenburg</site>
    <description>Lunenburg is the best surviving example of a planned British colonial settlement in North America. Established in 1753, it has retained its original layout and overall appearance, based on a rectangular grid pattern drawn up in the home country. The inhabitants have managed to safeguard the city's identity throughout the centuries by preserving the wooden architecture of the houses, some of which date from the 18th century.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="158" unique="176" trans="0" lat="49.74944444" long="-113.62388890">
    <criteria>(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1981</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Province of Alberta</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Head-Smashed-In Buffalo Jump</site>
    <description>In south-west Alberta, the remains of marked trails and an aboriginal camp, and a tumulus where vast quantities of buffalo (American Bison) skeletons can still be found, are evidence of a custom practised by aboriginal peoples of the North American plains for nearly 6,000 years. Using their excellent knowledge of the topography and of buffalo behaviour, they killed their prey by chasing them over a precipice; the carcasses were later carved up in the camp below.</description>
  </row>
   <row id="256" unique="286" trans="0" lat="59.35833333" long="-112.29333330">
    <criteria>(vii)(ix)(x)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1983</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Northwest Territories and Alberta</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Wood Buffalo National Park</site>
    <description>Situated on the plains in the north-central region of Canada, the park (which covers 44,807 km2) is home to North America's largest population of wild bison. It is also the natural nesting place of the whooping crane. Another of the park's attractions is the world's largest inland delta, located at the mouth of the Peace and Athabasca rivers.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="300" unique="336" trans="0" lat="46.80944444" long="-71.21055556">
    <criteria>(iv)(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1985</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Province of Quebec, City of Quebec</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Historic District of Old Québec</site>
    <description>Québec was founded by the French explorer Champlain in the early 17th century. It is the only North American city to have preserved its ramparts, together with the numerous bastions, gates and defensive works which still surround Old Québec. The Upper Town, built on the cliff, has remained the religious and administrative centre, with its churches, convents and other monuments like the Dauphine Redoubt, the Citadel and Château Frontenac. Together with the Lower Town and its ancient districts, it forms an urban ensemble which is one of the best examples of a fortified colonial city.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="304" unique="342" trans="0" lat="51.42472222" long="-116.47972220">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1984</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Provinces of British Columbia and Alberta</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Canadian Rocky Mountain Parks</site>
    <description>The contiguous national parks of Banff, Jasper, Kootenay and Yoho, as well as the Mount Robson, Mount Assiniboine and Hamber provincial parks, studded with mountain peaks, glaciers, lakes, waterfalls, canyons and limestone caves, form a striking mountain landscape. The Burgess Shale fossil site, well known for its fossil remains of soft-bodied marine animals, is also found there.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="419" unique="483" trans="0" lat="49.61250000" long="-57.53138889">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1987</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Provinces of Newfoundland and Labrador</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Gros Morne National Park</site>
    <description>Situated on the west coast of the island of Newfoundland, the park provides a rare example of the process of continental drift, where deep ocean crust and the rocks of the earth's mantle lie exposed. More recent glacial action has resulted in some spectacular scenery, with coastal lowland, alpine plateau, fjords, glacial valleys, sheer cliffs, waterfalls and many pristine lakes.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="686" unique="812" trans="0" lat="48.10500000" long="-66.35305556">
    <criteria>(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1999</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Gaspé Peninsula, Province of Quebec</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Miguasha National Park</site>
    <description>The palaeontological site of Miguasha National Park, in south-eastern Quebec on the southern coast of the Gaspé peninsula, is considered to be the world&amp;#39;s most outstanding illustration of the Devonian Period known as the &amp;#39;Age of Fishes&amp;#39;. Dating from 370 million years ago, the Upper Devonian Escuminac Formation represented here contains five of the six fossil fish groups associated with this period. Its significance stems from the discovery there of the highest number and best-preserved fossil specimens of the lobe-finned fishes that gave rise to the first four-legged, air-breathing terrestrial vertebrates – the tetrapods.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="1221" unique="1475" trans="0" lat="44.99438611" long="-75.76512500">
    <criteria>(i)(iv)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>2007</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Province of Ontario</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Rideau Canal</site>
    <description>The Rideau Canal, a monumental early 19th-century canal covering 202 kilometres of the Rideau and Cataraqui rivers from Ottawa south to Kingston Harbour on Lake Ontario was built primarily for strategic military purposes at a time when Great Britain and the United States of America vied for control of the region. The property, one of the first canals to be designed specifically for steam-powered vessels, also features an ensemble of fortifications. At the start of the project, in 1826, the British chose the so-called &amp;quot;slackwater&amp;quot; technology to avoid the need for extensive excavation. Instead, a series of dams were built to back up river water to a navigable depth and a chain of 47 massive locks were created. It is the best preserved example of a slackwater canal in North America demonstrating the use of this European technology in North America on a large scale. It is the only canal dating from the great North American canal-building era of the early 19th century to remain operational along its original line with most of its original structures intact. The canal was protected by the construction of six ‘blockhouses&amp;#39; and a fort. Defensible lockmaster&amp;#39;s houses were later added at several lock stations and, between 1846 and 1848 four Martello towers were constructed to strengthen the fortifications at Kingston harbour. The Rideau Canal is of historical importance as it bears witness to the fight for control of the north of the American Continent.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="4" unique="7" trans="0" lat="51.46666667" long="-55.61666667">
    <criteria>(vi)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1978</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Province of Newfoundland and Labrador</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>L’Anse aux Meadows National Historic Site</site>
    <description>At the tip of the Great Northern Peninsula of the island of Newfoundland, the remains of an 11th-century Viking settlement are evidence of the first European presence in North America. The excavated remains of wood-framed peat-turf buildings are similar to those found in Norse Greenland and Iceland.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="24" unique="27" trans="0" lat="61.54722222" long="-125.58944440">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1978</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Northwest Territories</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Nahanni National Park</site>
    <description>Located along the South Nahanni River, one of the most spectacular wild rivers in North America, this park contains deep canyons and huge waterfalls, as well as a unique limestone cave system. The park is also home to animals of the boreal forest, such as wolves, grizzly bears and caribou. Dall&amp;#39;s sheep and mountain goats are found in the park&amp;#39;s alpine environment.</description>
  </row>
  <row id="71" unique="75" trans="0" lat="50.76777778" long="-111.49222220">
    <criteria>(vii)(viii)</criteria>
    <inscribeDate>1979</inscribeDate>
    <code>ca</code>
    <region>North America</region>
    <location>Province of Alberta</location>
    <state>Canada</state>
    <site>Dinosaur Provincial Park</site>
    <description>In addition to its particularly beautiful scenery, Dinosaur Provincial Park – located at the heart of the province of Alberta's badlands – contains some of the most important fossil discoveries ever made from the 'Age of Reptiles', in particular about 35 species of dinosaur, dating back some 75 million years.</description>
  </row>
  </worldheritage>